<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-22T20:40:58+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Geo Imagine Developer</title><subtitle>script your own Earth</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Islands</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-islands/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Islands" /><published>2019-08-08T11:27:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-08T11:27:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-islands</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-islands/">&lt;p&gt;The Okavango swamps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/oka-tiles_wrs2_okaswamps_0_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 1. The Okavango Delta, Botswana; the figure shows the Landsat scenes used the ecoregion classification and the small inset images also shows the Okavango River Basin.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the late 1990’s the Geological Survey of Botswana used differential GPS (with cm accuracy) as part of a survey of the gravity of North-Eastern Botswana. The elevation data derived from this survey formed the baseline data for creating a Digital Elevation Model (DEM) and analysing &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.2113/1040243&quot;&gt;The topography of the Okavango Delta, Botswana, and its tectonic and sedimentological implications. (Gumbricht, T. McCarthy, T.S. &amp;amp; Merry, C.L., 2001) South African Journal of Geology, 104 (3) , 243-264.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;method-summary&quot;&gt;Method summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different datasets of point measured elevation data were assembled, quality checked and then transformed to the WGS84 datum and finally converted to orthometric heights using EGM96 (Earth Gravity Model 1996). Combining all the datasets, the larger Okavango region was divided along major fault lines, resulting in 4 sub-regions. For the sub-regions, individual DEMs where interpolated using kriging with manually fitted variograms, while also estimating the krigning standard deviation. Using a spatial filter kernel the four parts were smoothed across non-distinct boundaries and then combined. Contour lines were extracted and overlaid the &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;natural color landsat composite&lt;/a&gt;. Combining the DEM and the contour lines with other data, allowed us to analyze the topography of the palaeo-shorlines of lakes Ngami, Mababe and Mkgadikgadi, the relative elevation of water channels on the alluvial fan as well as other topographic relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elevation-datasets&quot;&gt;Elevation datasets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four different sources of point elevation data were used for interpolating a DEM in 500 m spatial resolution, table 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 1. Point elevation datasets used for creating the 500 m resolution Digital Elevation Model over the larger Okavango area.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Dataset&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;description&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt_gps-grav-survey_botswana_2000_bw-geosurvey.zip&quot;&gt;gps-grav-survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Gravity survey with differential GPS positioning&lt;br /&gt;Geological Survey of Botswana&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt_beacons_botswana_0_bw-maps.zip&quot;&gt;beacons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonemetric beacons identified from official Botswana maps&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;UCT-GPS&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Differential GPS positioning along major channels of the Okavango swamps&lt;br /&gt; University of Cape Town&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;DCW&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Beacon heights in the Namibian part of Linyanti&lt;br /&gt;Digital Chart of the World (DCW)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regionalization&quot;&gt;Regionalization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The larger Okavango region is clearly defined by fault lines, either trending North-West to South East (the Panhandle tectonic graben); or perpendicular to this direction and trending North-East to South-West (Gumare fault defining the transition from the Panhandle to the Okavango Alluvial Fan and the Kunyere and Thamalakane fault lines defining the terminal end of the alluvial fan). To accommodate the variations in elevation across the fault lines, we divided the larger Okavango area into four sub-regions for the geo-statistical interpolation, tables 2 and 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 2. Sub-regions used for constructing the DEM over the larger Okavango area
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Region&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rationale&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;NW-drylands&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Region North-West of the Kunyere fault line,&lt;br /&gt; excluding the Okavango Wetlands.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;SE-drylands&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Region South-East of the Thamalakane fault line,&lt;br /&gt; excluding the Boteti River Valley&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Kunyere-trappa&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The region between the Kunyere and Thamalakane fault lines&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Oka-wetlands&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The area of maximum flooding in the Okavango wetlands&lt;br /&gt; upstream of the Kunyere fault line (includes all channels&lt;br /&gt; transgressing the Kunyere-trappa as well as the Boteti River Valley)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 3. Okavango data layers of fault lines, river channels and elevation  regionalizations. The regionalization layer was constructed from the fault lines and channels layers, plus the flooding mask presented in the previous post. The data are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name int he table to download individual layers.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/support/fault-lines_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;fault-lines_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Fault lines&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/support/rivers-channels_karttur_okaswamps_0_digitized.zip&quot;&gt;rivers-channels_karttur_okaswamps_0_digitized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;River channels&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/geophysiology/geophysiology_wits_okaswamps_1994_pub.zip&quot;&gt;geophysiology_wits_okaswamps_1994_pub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geophysiological regions of the Okavango swmaps&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/support/elev-regions_karttur_okaswamps_0_4demcreate.zip&quot;&gt;elev-regions_karttur_okaswamps_0_4demcreate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation regions&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “NW-drylands” region is intersected by the Panhandle and includes the relict dune-fields west of the Okavango wetlands. The Western side of the Panhandel is uplifted compared to the Eastern side and the relict dunes have heights of approximately 10 meters. These variations where not considered when interpolating the DEM, and consequently the theoretical errors in “NW-drylands” region are comparatively large. The “SW-drylands” is defined as the region South-East of the Thamalakane fault line. It is the most data-poor region and the elevation estimates are poor over some parts of this region. The parallel Kunyere and Thamalakane fault lines define a stair between the Okavango wetlands and the SE-drylands. This stair, or “trappa”, define a third region: “kunyere-trappa”. Finally the Okavango wetlands (the maximum flooding area - see &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post) defines the central region: “oka-wetlands”. This region also include all the channels draining the Okavango swamps across the Linyanti-trappa and the Boteti River valley.
All regions have sections where the boundaries are less pronounced. For sections across sub-regions with no, or less, defined fault lines, nearby elevation points from the adjacent region were included in both regions spanning the boundary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to creating a DEM for the larger Okavango region, we also created three DEMs related to the palaeo-lakes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ngami&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mababe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mkgadikgadi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three are situated partly within and partly outside the area of the main map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;north-west-drylands&quot;&gt;North-West drylands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dryland region to the north west of the Thamalakane/Kunyere fault line (Figure 2), excluding the Okavango swamps and spanning both sides of the Panhandle entry channel, was interpolated using three combined datasets; GPS elevations from the gravity survey, beacon heights drawn from Botswana maps and heights from the Digital Chart of the World (DCW), table 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 3. Elevation point data sources used for interpolating the region &quot;NW-drylands&quot; (see figure 1). All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS surveyed elevations&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonometric beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_dcw_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_dcw_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Digital Chart of World heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;south-east-drylands&quot;&gt;South-East drylands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The south eastern region (“SE-drylands”), on the uplifted side of the Thamalakane fault and intersected by the Boteti valley, was interpolated using GPS elevations from the gravity survey and beacons identified from Botswana maps, table 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 4. Elevation point data sources used for interpolating the region &quot;SE-drylands&quot; (see figure 2). All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the bottom of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS surveyed elevation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonometric beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kunyere-trappa-region&quot;&gt;Kunyere trappa region&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The region between the Kunyere and Thamalakane faults lines (“kunyere-trappa”) (figure 2) was interpolated separately. The region is intersected by the rivers draining the distal arms of the Okavango swamps before they join the Thamalakane River (defined by the Thamalakane fault line). The “Kunyere-trappa” region was interpolated using GPS elevations from the GPS/gravity survey and trigonometric beacon heights from Botswana maps, table 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 5. Elevation point data sources used for interpolating the region &quot;kunyere-trappa&quot; (see figure 1). All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum (**not** the Cape datum as in the scientific article, the data has been reprojected to a more standardized format). All layers are available for download [here](), or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS surveyed elevation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonometric beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;okavango-wetlands-region&quot;&gt;Okavango wetlands region&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last, central, region is the maximum flood area (see &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post) of the Okavango wetlands, and the region is called “oka-wetlands”. To interpolate this region we used three different data sets; GPS elevations the gravity survey, beacons from Botswana maps and GPS points collected by University of Cape Town (UCT), table 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 6. Elevation point data sources used for interpolating the region &quot;NW-drylands&quot; (see figure 1). All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum  All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS surveyed elevation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonometric beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-uct_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-uct_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS survey by University of Cape Town&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;unused-trigonometric-heights&quot;&gt;Unused trigonometric heights&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all trigonometric beacon heights identified in various Botswana maps were used. For completeness, also the unused elevation points are supplied here, table 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 7. Identified, but unused, trigonometric beacon heights. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-unused_beacons_okaswamps_2000_all-regions.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-unused_beacons_okaswamps_2000_all-regions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Unused beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okavango-dem&quot;&gt;Okavango DEM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DEM for the larger Okavango region was created by combining the four regional DEMs and then smoothing the compositional DEM across areas with no pronounced faults (for details please see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.2113/1040243&quot;&gt;original article&lt;/a&gt;). A few pronounced heights and troughs were added, and the elevation contour lines extracted. The final DEM, as a 50 mm raster and as contour lines are listed and available for download in table 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 8. Spatial data layers available for the larger Okavango region. All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layer&lt;/strong&gt; (shape file)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/okaswamps/elev-contours_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-contours_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation contour lines for the larger Okavango area.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/okaswamps/dem_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geo-interpoalted DEM in 500 m spatial resolution&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/okaswamps/dem-sd_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-sd_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Estimated error (1 standard deviation)&lt;br /&gt; of the interpolated DEM&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-okavango-alluvial-fan&quot;&gt;The Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Okavango Alluvial Fan (Figure 3), forms an almost perfectly shaped cone but where small variations potentially could reveal sedimentation, erosion or tectonic movements. To compare the modeled DEM with a theoretical cone, several spatial entities related to the Okavango Alluvial Fan where identified or created, table 9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 9. Spatial data layers associated with Okavango the Alluvial Fan. All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/alluvialfan/alluvial-fan-apex_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan-apex_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The apex (beginning, point from spreading out)&lt;br /&gt; of the Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/alluvialfan/alluvial-fan_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The surface area of the Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/alluvialfan/alluvial-fan-isodist_karttur_okaswamps_0_fromapex.zip&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan-isodist_karttur_okaswamps_0_fromapex&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Iso-distance lines (25 km interval) from the apex&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/alluvialfan/alluvial-fan-cone-dem_karttur_okasvamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan-cone-dem_karttur_okasvamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Idealized, perfectly cone shaped DEM&lt;br /&gt; over the Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/alluvialfan/alluvial-fan-residual-dem_karttur_okasvamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan-residual-dem_karttur_okasvamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;elevation difference between the idealized and&lt;br /&gt; the interpolated DEMs over the Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lake-ngami-region&quot;&gt;Lake Ngami Region&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted above, a special DEM was created for Lake Ngami and its surroundings. The palaeo shorelines of Lake Ngami were omitted from the DEM that thus shows the base level of these shorelines. Extracting the base levels we could analyse the topography of the shorelines. The results indicate that the palaeo shorelines are tilted towards north-east, indicating tectonic movements (sagging) since palaeo Lake Ngami dried out. All the data for the Lake Ngami DEM are listed in table 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 10. Spatial data layers available for the Lake Ngami Region. All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layers&lt;/strong&gt; (shape files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/centreline_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;centreline_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The central axis of Lake Ngami&lt;br /&gt; (for analysing tilting)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/elev-contours_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-contours_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation contour lines for the Lake Ngami basin, &lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;disregarding&lt;/em&gt; any ridges (i.e. palaeo-shorelines)&lt;br /&gt; or channels.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation point data (best estimate and error)&lt;br /&gt;  extracted from the generated DEM (GeoTiff)&lt;br /&gt;for the base level of Lake Ngami palaeo-shorelines.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/elev-pt_beacons_lakengami_0_frommap.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt_beacons_lakengami_0_frommap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Input elevation data from existing beacons,&lt;br /&gt; used for the geo-interolation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/elev-pt_gps_lakengami_1999_grav-survey.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt_gps_lakengami_1999_grav-survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Input elevation data from a precision&lt;br /&gt;gravity/GPS survey, used for the geo-interolation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/isodist_karttur_lakengami_0_centreline.zip&quot;&gt;isodist_karttur_lakengami_0_centreline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Distances along the central axis (see top row)&lt;br /&gt; for defining proximity (tilting) along palaeo-shoreliens&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/palaeo-shore-line_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;palaeo-shore-line_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Lake Ngami palaeo shorlines&lt;br /&gt; interpreted from &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;Landsat image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/dem_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geo-interpoalted DEM in 500 m spatial resolution&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/dem-sd_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-sd_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Estimated error (1 standard deviation) of the interpolated DEM&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/natcol_lt05_lakengami_199407_byte.tif.zip&quot;&gt;natcol_lt05_lakengami_199407_byte&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Natural color Landsat TM image&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mababe-depression-region&quot;&gt;Mababe Depression Region&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The special DEM for the Mababe depression was done using only the gravity GPS surveyed elevations points. The DEM for the Mababe depression excludes all local ridges, including the palaeo shoreline defining palaeo Lake Mababe. Water channels, including the drainage connecting Mababe Depression with both the Linyanti and Okavango swamps are also excluded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results indicate that the palaeo shorelines are tilted towards south-west, which is exactly opposite the tilting of the shorelines of Lake Ngami. This suggests that the region between the two palaeo-lakes must have sunken since the lakes died out. In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.2113/1040243&quot;&gt;scientific article&lt;/a&gt; we speculate that this depends on sagging due to the shear weight of the sediments deposited over the Okavango Alluvial Fan. All the data for the Mababe depression DEM are listed in table 11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 11. Spatial data layers available for the Mababe Depression Region. All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layers&lt;/strong&gt; (shape files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/centreline_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;centreline_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The central axis of Mababe Depression&lt;br /&gt; (for analysing tilting)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/elev-contours_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-contours_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation contour lines for the Mababe Depression, &lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;disregarding&lt;/em&gt; any ridges (i.e. palaeo-shorelines)&lt;br /&gt; or channels.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation point data (best estimate and error)&lt;br /&gt;  extracted from the generated DEM (GeoTiff)&lt;br /&gt;for the base level of Mababe Depression palaeo-shorelines.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/elev-pt_gps_mababedepr_1999_grav-survey.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt_gps_mababedepr_1999_grav-survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Input elevation data from a precision&lt;br /&gt;gravity/GPS survey, used for the geo-interolation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/isodist_karttur_mababedepr_0_centreline.zip&quot;&gt;isodist_karttur_mababedepr_0_centreline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Distances along the central axis (see top row)&lt;br /&gt; for defining proximity (tilting) along palaeo-shoreliens&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/palaeo-shore-line_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;palaeo-shore-line_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Mababe Depression palaeo shorlines&lt;br /&gt; interpreted from &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;Landsat image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/dem_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geo-interpoalted DEM in 500 m spatial resolution&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/dem-sd_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-sd_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Estimated error (1 standard deviation) of the interpolated DEM&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_byte.tif.zip&quot;&gt;natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_byte&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Natural color Landsat TM image&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mkgadikgadi-ridge-region&quot;&gt;Mkgadikgadi Ridge Region&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The special DEM for the Mkgadikgadi Ridge was done using only the gravity GPS surveyed elevations points. The DEM for the Mkgadikgadi Ridge region excludes all local ridges, including the Mkgadikgadi Ridge (Lake Mkgadikgadi palaeo shoreline) itself. Also water channels, including the drainage along the Boteti River are excluded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results indicate that the palaeo shoreline is not level with the geoid but has a dip that is at its deepest exactly along the central axis of the Okavango Alluvial Fan. This corroborates the hypothesis that sagging has caused the tectonic depressions along the central axis of the Okavango Alluvial Fan, including the Pnahandle entry channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When restoring the data in July 2019 (almost 20 years after the work was done), the layer for the estimated DEM confidence level (dem-sd_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_pub.tif) had one row and one column less compared to the interpolated DEM itself (dem_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_pub.tif). I could not find the reason, and the layers available thus differ in size. All the data for the Mkgadikgadi Ridge Region DEM are listed in table 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 12. Spatial data layers available for the Mkgadikgadi Ridge Region. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layers&lt;/strong&gt; (shape files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/elev-contours_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-contours_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Elevation contour lines for the Makgadikgadi Ridge region, &lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;disregarding&lt;/em&gt; any ridges (i.e. palaeo-shorelines)&lt;br /&gt; or channels.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Elevation point data (best estimate and error)&lt;br /&gt;  extracted from the generated DEM (GeoTiff)&lt;br /&gt;for the base level of Makgadikgadi [id]: url “title”idge (palaeo-shoreline).&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/elev-pt_gps_mkgadiridge_1999_grav-survey.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt_gps_mkgadiridge_1999_grav-survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Input elevation data from a precision&lt;br /&gt;gravity/GPS survey, used for the geo-interolation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/isodist_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_paleoshoreline.zip&quot;&gt;isodist_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_paleoshoreline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Distances along the palaeo shore line&lt;br /&gt; for defining proximity (tilting)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/palaeo-shore-line_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;palaeo-shore-line_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Makgadikgadi palaeo shorlines&lt;br /&gt; interpreted from &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;Landsat image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/dem_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Geo-interpoalted DEM in 500 m spatial resolution&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/dem-sd_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-sd_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Estimated error (1 standard deviation) of the interpolated DEM&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/natcol_lt05_mkgadiridge_199407_byte.tif.zip&quot;&gt;natcol_lt05_mkgadiridge_199407_byte&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Natural color Landsat TM image&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okavango-swamps-water-level-dem&quot;&gt;Okavango swamps water level DEM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survey campaigns conducted by University of Cape Town (UCT) during 1994, 1995, 1996 and 1998 also included measurements of the elevation of surface water, table 13. The 1995 campaign was the most extensive. Using sites with overlapping elevations, all the UCT surface water level data was linearly transferred to represent the 1995 situation. The adjusted elevation data was then used for constructing a surface water table DEM for the Okavango wetlands, table 13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layers&lt;/strong&gt; (shape files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1994_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1994_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Water surface elevation from the UCT 1994 campaign.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1995_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1995_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Water surface elevation from the UCT 1995 campaign.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1996_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1996_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Water surface elevation from the UCT 1996 campaign.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1998_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1998_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Water surface elevation from the UCT 1998 campaign.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layer&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/dem-water-surface_karttur_okaswamp_1995_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-water-surface_karttur_okaswamp_1995_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;DEM for the Okavango water table&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevation point data used as input for generating DEM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/surfacewater/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water surface elevation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/geophysiology/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geophysiological regions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgement&quot;&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work was done as part on an international co-operation within the Okavango Research Group headed by prof. T.S.McCarthy, Department of Geology, Wits University. My post doctoral scholarship was financed by the Swedish Royal Academy of Sciences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Okavango" /><category term="islands" /><summary type="html">Islands of the Okavango wetlands</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/avg-trmm-3b43v7-precip_3B43_trmm_2001-2016_A" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Regional topography</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-dem_v2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Regional topography" /><published>2019-07-18T11:27:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-18T11:27:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-dem_v2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-dem_v2/">&lt;p&gt;Over a distance of 240 km, from the top of the Panhandle entry channel and down to the Kunyere fault defining the terminal end of the alluvial fan, the drop in elevation over the Okavango swamps, Botswana, is approximately 60 m, Figure 1. The topographic variations in the surface of the Okavango Alluvial Fan is extremely subtle but still defines the distribution of water and wetlands over the surface of the Alluvial Fan. Over decades to centuries changes in topography, driven both by the sedimentation associated with the active channels and tectonic movements, alter the topography and consequently also the distribution of wetlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent my Post Doc years (1999-2001) at University of the Witwatersrand (Johannesburg, South Africa) studying the Okavango swamps. My supervisor, prof. T.S. McCarthy got hold of data from a gravity survey over Botswana that also included differential GPS elevations. From that data we constructed a topographic map over the larger Okavango area. This post summarizes the study on the topography of the Okavango Delta, and also links to the data presented in the published article. If you are only interested in the data, the links to the online repositories are given at the end of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/oka-tiles_wrs2_okaswamps_0_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 1. The Okavango Delta, Botswana; the figure shows the Landsat scenes used the ecoregion classification and the small inset images also shows the Okavango River Basin.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the late 1990’s the Geological Survey of Botswana used differential GPS (with cm accuracy) as part of a survey of the gravity of North-Eastern Botswana. The elevation data derived from this survey formed the baseline data for creating a Digital Elevation Model (DEM) and analysing &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.2113/1040243&quot;&gt;The topography of the Okavango Delta, Botswana, and its tectonic and sedimentological implications. (Gumbricht, T. McCarthy, T.S. &amp;amp; Merry, C.L., 2001) South African Journal of Geology, 104 (3) , 243-264.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;method-summary&quot;&gt;Method summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different datasets of point measured elevation data were assembled, quality checked and then transformed to the WGS84 datum and finally converted to orthometric heights using EGM96 (Earth Gravity Model 1996). Combining all the datasets, the larger Okavango region was divided along major fault lines, resulting in 4 sub-regions. For the sub-regions, individual DEMs where interpolated using kriging with manually fitted variograms, while also estimating the krigning standard deviation. Using a spatial filter kernel the four parts were smoothed across non-distinct boundaries and then combined. Contour lines were extracted and overlaid the &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;natural color landsat composite&lt;/a&gt;. Combining the DEM and the contour lines with other data allowed us to analyze the topography of the palaeo-shorlines of lakes Ngami, Mababe and Mkgadikgadi, the relative elevation of water channels on the alluvial fan as well as other topographic relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elevation-datasets&quot;&gt;Elevation datasets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four different sources of point elevation data were used for interpolating a DEM in 500 m spatial resolution, table 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 1. Point elevation datasets used for creating the 500 m resolution Digital Elevation Model over the larger Okavango area.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Dataset&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt_gps-grav-survey_botswana_2000_bw-geosurvey.zip&quot;&gt;gps-grav-survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Gravity survey with differential GPS positioning&lt;br /&gt;Geological Survey of Botswana&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt_beacons_botswana_0_bw-maps.zip&quot;&gt;beacons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonemetric beacons identified from official Botswana maps&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;UCT-GPS&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Differential GPS positioning along major channels of the Okavango swamps&lt;br /&gt; University of Cape Town&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;DCW&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Beacon heights in the Namibian part of Linyanti&lt;br /&gt;Digital Chart of the World (DCW)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regionalization&quot;&gt;Regionalization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The larger Okavango region is clearly defined by fault lines, either trending North-West to South East (the Panhandle tectonic graben); or perpendicular to this direction and trending North-East to South-West (Gumare fault defining the transition from the Panhandle to the Okavango Alluvial Fan and the Kunyere and Thamalakane fault lines defining the terminal end of the alluvial fan). To accommodate the variations in elevation across the fault lines, we divided the larger Okavango area into four sub-regions for the geo-statistical interpolation, tables 2 and 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 2. Sub-regions used for constructing the DEM over the larger Okavango area
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Region&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rationale&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;NW-drylands&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Region North-West of the Kunyere fault line,&lt;br /&gt; excluding the Okavango Wetlands.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;SE-drylands&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Region South-East of the Thamalakane fault line,&lt;br /&gt; excluding the Boteti River Valley.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Kunyere-trappa&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The region between the Kunyere and Thamalakane fault lines.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Oka-wetlands&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The area of maximum flooding in the Okavango wetlands&lt;br /&gt; upstream of the Kunyere fault line (includes all channels&lt;br /&gt; transgressing the Kunyere-trappa as well as the Boteti River Valley).&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 3. Okavango data layers of fault lines, river channels and elevation  regionalizations. The regionalization layer was constructed from the fault lines and channels layers, plus the flooding mask presented in an earlier post. The data are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name int he table to download individual layers.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/support/fault-lines_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;fault-lines_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Fault lines&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/support/rivers-channels_karttur_okaswamps_0_digitized.zip&quot;&gt;rivers-channels_karttur_okaswamps_0_digitized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;River channels&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/geophysiology/geophysiology_wits_okaswamps_1994_pub.zip&quot;&gt;geophysiology_wits_okaswamps_1994_pub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geophysiological regions of the Okavango swmaps&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/support/elev-regions_karttur_okaswamps_0_4demcreate.zip&quot;&gt;elev-regions_karttur_okaswamps_0_4demcreate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation regions&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “NW-drylands” region is intersected by the Panhandle and includes the relict dune-fields west of the Okavango wetlands. The Western side of the Panhandel is uplifted compared to the Eastern side and the relict dunes have heights of approximately 10 meters. These variations where not considered when interpolating the DEM, and consequently the theoretical errors in “NW-drylands” region are comparatively large. The “SW-drylands” is defined as the region South-East of the Thamalakane fault line. It is the most data-poor region and the elevation estimates are poor over some parts of this region. The parallel Kunyere and Thamalakane fault lines define a stair between the Okavango wetlands and the SE-drylands. This stair, or “trappa”, define a third region: “kunyere-trappa”. Finally the Okavango wetlands (the maximum flooding area - see &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post) defines the central region: “oka-wetlands”. This region also include all the channels draining the Okavango swamps across the Linyanti-trappa and the Boteti River valley.
All regions have sections where the boundaries are less pronounced. For sections across sub-regions with no, or less, defined fault lines, nearby elevation points from the adjacent region were included in both regions spanning the boundary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to creating a DEM for the larger Okavango region, we also created three DEMs related to the palaeo-lakes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ngami&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mababe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mkgadikgadi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three are situated partly within and partly outside the area of the main map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;north-west-drylands&quot;&gt;North-West drylands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dryland region to the north west (“NW-drylands”) of the Thamalakane/Kunyere fault line (Figure 2), excluding the Okavango swamps and spanning both sides of the Panhandle entry channel, was interpolated using three combined datasets; GPS elevations from the gravity survey, beacon heights drawn from Botswana maps and heights from the Digital Chart of the World (DCW), table 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 3. Elevation point data sources used for interpolating the region &quot;NW-drylands&quot; (see figure 1). All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS surveyed elevations&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonometric beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_dcw_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_dcw_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Digital Chart of World heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;south-east-drylands&quot;&gt;South-East drylands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The south eastern region (“SE-drylands”), on the uplifted side of the Thamalakane fault and intersected by the Boteti valley, was interpolated using GPS elevations from the gravity survey and beacons identified from Botswana maps, table 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 4. Elevation point data sources used for interpolating the region &quot;SE-drylands&quot; (see figure 2). All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the bottom of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS surveyed elevation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonometric beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kunyere-trappa-region&quot;&gt;Kunyere trappa region&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The region between the Kunyere and Thamalakane fault lines (“kunyere-trappa”) (figure 2) was interpolated separately. The region is intersected by the rivers draining the distal arms of the Okavango swamps before they join the Thamalakane River (defined by the Thamalakane fault line). The “Kunyere-trappa” region was interpolated using GPS elevations from the GPS/gravity survey and trigonometric beacon heights from Botswana maps, table 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 5. Elevation point data sources used for interpolating the region &quot;kunyere-trappa&quot; (see figure 2). All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the bottom of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS surveyed elevation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonometric beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;okavango-wetlands-region&quot;&gt;Okavango wetlands region&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last, central, region is the maximum flood area (see &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post) of the Okavango wetlands, and the region is called “oka-wetlands”. To interpolate this region we used three different data sets; GPS elevations the gravity survey, beacons from Botswana maps and GPS points collected by University of Cape Town (UCT), table 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 6. Elevation point data sources used for interpolating the region &quot;oka-wetlands&quot; (see figure 2). All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum  All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS surveyed elevation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonometric beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-uct_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-uct_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS survey by University of Cape Town&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;unused-trigonometric-heights&quot;&gt;Unused trigonometric heights&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all trigonometric beacon heights identified in various Botswana maps were used. For completeness, also the unused elevation points are supplied here, table 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 7. Identified, but unused, trigonometric beacon heights. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-unused_beacons_okaswamps_2000_all-regions.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-unused_beacons_okaswamps_2000_all-regions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Unused beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okavango-dem&quot;&gt;Okavango DEM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DEM for the larger Okavango region was created by combining the four regional DEMs and then smoothing the compositional DEM across areas with no pronounced faults (for details please see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.2113/1040243&quot;&gt;original article&lt;/a&gt;). A few pronounced heights and troughs were added, and the elevation contour lines extracted. The final DEM, as a 500 m raster and as contour lines are listed and available for download in table 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 8. Elevation data layers available for the larger Okavango region. All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layer&lt;/strong&gt; (shape file)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/okaswamps/elev-contours_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-contours_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation contour lines for the larger Okavango area.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/okaswamps/dem_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geo-interpoalted DEM in 500 m spatial resolution&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/okaswamps/dem-sd_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-sd_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Estimated error (1 standard deviation)&lt;br /&gt; of the interpolated DEM&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-okavango-alluvial-fan&quot;&gt;The Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Okavango Alluvial Fan (Figure 3), forms an almost perfectly shaped cone where small variations potentially could reveal sedimentation, erosion or tectonic movements. To compare the interpolated DEM with a theoretical cone, several spatial entities related to the Okavango Alluvial Fan were identified or created, table 9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 9. Spatial data layers associated with Okavango the Alluvial Fan. All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/alluvialfan/alluvial-fan-apex_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan-apex_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The apex (beginning, point from spreading out)&lt;br /&gt; of the Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/alluvialfan/alluvial-fan_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The surface area of the Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/alluvialfan/alluvial-fan-isodist_karttur_okaswamps_0_fromapex.zip&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan-isodist_karttur_okaswamps_0_fromapex&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Iso-distance lines (25 km interval) from the apex&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/alluvialfan/alluvial-fan-cone-dem_karttur_okasvamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan-cone-dem_karttur_okasvamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Idealized, perfectly cone shaped DEM&lt;br /&gt; over the Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/alluvialfan/alluvial-fan-residual-dem_karttur_okasvamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan-residual-dem_karttur_okasvamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;elevation difference between the idealized and&lt;br /&gt; the interpolated DEMs over the Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lake-ngami-region&quot;&gt;Lake Ngami Region&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted above, a special DEM was created for Lake Ngami and its surroundings. The palaeo shorelines of Lake Ngami were omitted from the DEM, that thus shows the base level of these shorelines. Extracting the base levels we could analyse the topography of the shorelines. The results indicate that the palaeo shorelines are tilted towards north-east, indicating tectonic movements (sagging) since palaeo Lake Ngami dried out. All the data for the Lake Ngami DEM analysis are listed in table 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 10. Spatial data layers available for the Lake Ngami Region. All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layers&lt;/strong&gt; (shape files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/centreline_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;centreline_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The central axis of Lake Ngami&lt;br /&gt; (for analysing tilting)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/elev-contours_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-contours_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation contour lines for the Lake Ngami basin, &lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;disregarding&lt;/em&gt; any ridges (i.e. palaeo-shorelines)&lt;br /&gt; or channels.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation point data (best estimate and error)&lt;br /&gt;  extracted from the generated DEM (GeoTiff)&lt;br /&gt;for the base level of Lake Ngami palaeo-shorelines.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/elev-pt_beacons_lakengami_0_frommap.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt_beacons_lakengami_0_frommap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Input elevation data from existing beacons,&lt;br /&gt; used for the geo-interolation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/elev-pt_gps_lakengami_1999_grav-survey.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt_gps_lakengami_1999_grav-survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Input elevation data from a precision&lt;br /&gt;gravity/GPS survey, used for the geo-interolation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/isodist_karttur_lakengami_0_centreline.zip&quot;&gt;isodist_karttur_lakengami_0_centreline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Distances along the central axis (see top row)&lt;br /&gt; for defining proximity (tilting) along palaeo-shoreliens&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/palaeo-shore-line_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;palaeo-shore-line_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Lake Ngami palaeo shorlines&lt;br /&gt; interpreted from &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;Landsat image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/dem_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geo-interpoalted DEM in 500 m spatial resolution&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/dem-sd_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-sd_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Estimated error (1 standard deviation) of the interpolated DEM&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/natcol_lt05_lakengami_199407_byte.tif.zip&quot;&gt;natcol_lt05_lakengami_199407_byte&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Natural color Landsat TM image&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mababe-depression-region&quot;&gt;Mababe Depression Region&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The special DEM for the Mababe depression was done using only the gravity GPS surveyed elevations points. The DEM for the Mababe depression excludes all local ridges, including the palaeo shoreline defining palaeo Lake Mababe. Water channels, including the drainage connecting Mababe Depression with both the Linyanti and Okavango swamps are also excluded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results indicate that the palaeo shorelines are tilted towards south-west, which is exactly opposite the tilting of the shorelines of Lake Ngami. This suggests that the region between the two palaeo-lakes must have sunken since the lakes died out. In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.2113/1040243&quot;&gt;scientific article&lt;/a&gt; we speculate that this depends on sagging due to the shear weight of the sediments deposited over the Okavango Alluvial Fan. All the data for the Mababe depression DEM are listed in table 11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 11. Spatial data layers available for the Mababe Depression Region. All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layers&lt;/strong&gt; (shape files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/centreline_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;centreline_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The central axis of Mababe Depression&lt;br /&gt; (for analysing tilting)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/elev-contours_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-contours_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation contour lines for the Mababe Depression, &lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;disregarding&lt;/em&gt; any ridges (i.e. palaeo-shorelines)&lt;br /&gt; or channels.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation point data (best estimate and error)&lt;br /&gt;  extracted from the generated DEM (GeoTiff)&lt;br /&gt;for the base level of Mababe Depression palaeo-shorelines.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/elev-pt_gps_mababedepr_1999_grav-survey.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt_gps_mababedepr_1999_grav-survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Input elevation data from a precision&lt;br /&gt;gravity/GPS survey, used for the geo-interolation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/isodist_karttur_mababedepr_0_centreline.zip&quot;&gt;isodist_karttur_mababedepr_0_centreline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Distances along the central axis (see top row)&lt;br /&gt; for defining proximity (tilting) along palaeo-shoreliens&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/palaeo-shore-line_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;palaeo-shore-line_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Mababe Depression palaeo shorlines&lt;br /&gt; interpreted from &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;Landsat image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/dem_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geo-interpoalted DEM in 500 m spatial resolution&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/dem-sd_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-sd_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Estimated error (1 standard deviation) of the interpolated DEM&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_byte.tif.zip&quot;&gt;natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_byte&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Natural color Landsat TM image&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mkgadikgadi-ridge-region&quot;&gt;Mkgadikgadi Ridge Region&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The special DEM for the Mkgadikgadi Ridge was done using only the gravity GPS surveyed elevations points. The DEM for the Mkgadikgadi Ridge region excludes all local ridges, including the Mkgadikgadi Ridge (Lake Mkgadikgadi palaeo shoreline) itself. Also water channels, including the drainage along the Boteti River are excluded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results indicate that the palaeo shoreline is not level with the geoid but has a dip that is at its deepest exactly along the central axis of the Okavango Alluvial Fan. This corroborates the hypothesis that sagging has caused the tectonic depressions along the central axis of the Okavango Alluvial Fan, including the Panhandle entry channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When restoring the data in July 2019 (almost 20 years after the work was done), the layer for the estimated DEM confidence level (dem-sd_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_pub.tif) had one row and one column less compared to the interpolated DEM itself (dem_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_pub.tif). I could not find the reason, and the layers available thus differ in size. All the data for the Mkgadikgadi Ridge Region DEM are listed in table 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 12. Spatial data layers available for the Mkgadikgadi Ridge Region. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layers&lt;/strong&gt; (shape files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/elev-contours_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-contours_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Elevation contour lines for the Makgadikgadi Ridge region, &lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;disregarding&lt;/em&gt; any ridges (i.e. palaeo-shorelines)&lt;br /&gt; or channels.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Elevation point data (best estimate and error)&lt;br /&gt;  extracted from the generated DEM (GeoTiff)&lt;br /&gt;for the base level of Makgadikgadi [id]: url “title”idge (palaeo-shoreline).&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/elev-pt_gps_mkgadiridge_1999_grav-survey.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt_gps_mkgadiridge_1999_grav-survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Input elevation data from a precision&lt;br /&gt;gravity/GPS survey, used for the geo-interolation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/isodist_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_paleoshoreline.zip&quot;&gt;isodist_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_paleoshoreline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Distances along the palaeo shore line&lt;br /&gt; for defining proximity (tilting)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/palaeo-shore-line_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;palaeo-shore-line_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Makgadikgadi palaeo shorlines&lt;br /&gt; interpreted from &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;Landsat image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/dem_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Geo-interpoalted DEM in 500 m spatial resolution&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/dem-sd_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-sd_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Estimated error (1 standard deviation) of the interpolated DEM&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/natcol_lt05_mkgadiridge_199407_byte.tif.zip&quot;&gt;natcol_lt05_mkgadiridge_199407_byte&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Natural color Landsat TM image&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okavango-swamps-water-level-dem&quot;&gt;Okavango swamps water level DEM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survey campaigns conducted by University of Cape Town (UCT) during 1994, 1995, 1996 and 1998 also included measurements of the elevation of surface water, table 13. The 1995 campaign was the most extensive. Using sites with overlapping elevations, all the UCT surface water level data was linearly transferred to represent the 1995 situation. The adjusted elevation data was then used for constructing a surface water table DEM for the Okavango wetlands, table 13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layers&lt;/strong&gt; (shape files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1994_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1994_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Water surface elevation from the UCT 1994 campaign.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1995_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1995_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Water surface elevation from the UCT 1995 campaign.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1996_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1996_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Water surface elevation from the UCT 1996 campaign.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1998_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1998_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Water surface elevation from the UCT 1998 campaign.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layer&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/dem-water-surface_karttur_okaswamp_1995_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-water-surface_karttur_okaswamp_1995_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;DEM for the Okavango water table&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevation point data used as input for generating DEM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/surfacewater/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water surface elevation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/geophysiology/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geophysiological regions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgement&quot;&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work was done as part on an international co-operation within the Okavango Research Group headed by prof. T.S.McCarthy, Department of Geology, Wits University. My post doctoral scholarship was financed by the Swedish Royal Academy of Sciences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Okavango" /><category term="topography" /><category term="tectonics" /><category term="Earth mocvements" /><summary type="html">Creating a regional Digital Elevation Model for the Okavango Delta, Botswana</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/avg-trmm-3b43v7-precip_3B43_trmm_2001-2016_A" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Regional topography</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-dem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Regional topography" /><published>2019-07-18T11:27:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-18T11:27:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-dem</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-dem/">&lt;p&gt;Over a distance of 240 km, from the top of the Panhandle entry channel and down to the Kunyere fault defining the terminal end of the alluvial fan, the drop in elevation over the Okavango swamps, Botswana, is approximately 60 m, Figure 1. Even if the topographic variations in the surface of the Okavango Alluvial Fan is extremely subtle, it still defines the distribution of water and wetlands over the surface of the Alluvial Fan. Over decades to centuries changes in topography, driven both by the sedimentation associated with the active channels and tectonic movements, alter the topography and consequently also the distribution of wetlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent my Post Doc years (1999-2001) at University of the Witwatersrand (Johannesburg, South Africa) studying the Okavango swamps. My supervisor, prof. T.S. McCarthy got hold of data from a gravity survey over Botswana that also included differential GPS elevations. From that data we constructed a topographic map over the larger Okavango area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post summarizes the study on the topography of the Okavango Delta, and also links to the data presented in the published article. If you are only interested in the data, the link to the online repository is given at the end of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/oka-tiles_wrs2_okaswamps_0_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 1. The Okavango Delta, Botswana; the figure shows the Landsat scenes used the ecoregion classification and the small inset images also shows the Okavango River Basin.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the late 1990’s the Geological Survey of Botswana used differential GPS (with cm accuracy) as part of a survey of the gravity of North-Eastern Botswana. The elevation data derived from this survey formed the baseline data for creating a Digital Elevation Model (DEM) and analysing &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.2113/1040243&quot;&gt;The topography of the Okavango Delta, Botswana, and its tectonic and sedimentological implications. (Gumbricht, T. McCarthy, T.S. &amp;amp; Merry, C.L., 2001) South African Journal of Geology, 104 (3) , 243-264.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;method-summary&quot;&gt;Method summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different datasets of point measured elevation data were assembled, quality checked and then transformed to the WGS84 datum and finally converted to orthometric heights using EGM96 (Earth Gravity Model 1996). Combining all the datasets, the larger Okavango region was divided along major fault lines, resulting in 4 sub-regions. For the sub-regions, individual DEMs where interpolated using kriging with manually fitted variograms, while also estimating the krigning standard deviation. Using a spatial filter kernel the four parts were smoothed across non-distinct boundaries and then combined. Contour lines were extracted and overlaid the &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;natural color landsat composite&lt;/a&gt;. Combining the DEM and the contour lines with other data allowed us to analyze the topography of the palaeo-shorlines of lakes Ngami, Mababe and Mkgadikgadi, the relative elevation of water channels on the alluvial fan as well as other topographic relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elevation-datasets&quot;&gt;Elevation datasets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four different sources of point elevation data were used for interpolating a DEM in 500 m spatial resolution, table 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 1. Point elevation datasets used for creating the 500 m resolution Digital Elevation Model over the larger Okavango area.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Dataset&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt_gps-grav-survey_botswana_2000_bw-geosurvey.zip&quot;&gt;gps-grav-survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Gravity survey with differential GPS positioning&lt;br /&gt;Geological Survey of Botswana&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt_beacons_botswana_0_bw-maps.zip&quot;&gt;beacons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonemetric beacons identified from official Botswana maps&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;UCT-GPS&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Differential GPS positioning along major channels of the Okavango swamps&lt;br /&gt; University of Cape Town&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;DCW&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Beacon heights in the Namibian part of Linyanti&lt;br /&gt;Digital Chart of the World (DCW)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regionalization&quot;&gt;Regionalization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The larger Okavango region is clearly defined by fault lines, either trending North-West to South East (the Panhandle tectonic graben); or perpendicular to this direction and trending North-East to South-West (Gumare fault defining the transition from the Panhandle to the Okavango Alluvial Fan and the Kunyere and Thamalakane fault lines defining the terminal end of the alluvial fan). To accommodate the variations in elevation across the fault lines, we divided the larger Okavango area into four sub-regions for the geo-statistical interpolation, tables 2 and 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 2. Sub-regions used for constructing the DEM over the larger Okavango area.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Region&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rationale&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;NW-drylands&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Region North-West of the Kunyere fault line,&lt;br /&gt; excluding the Okavango Wetlands.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;SE-drylands&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Region South-East of the Thamalakane fault line,&lt;br /&gt; excluding the Boteti River Valley.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Kunyere-trappa&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The region between the Kunyere and Thamalakane fault lines.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Oka-wetlands&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The area of maximum flooding in the Okavango wetlands&lt;br /&gt; upstream of the Kunyere fault line (includes all channels&lt;br /&gt; transgressing the Kunyere-trappa as well as the Boteti River Valley).&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 3. Okavango data layers of fault lines, river channels and elevation regionalizations. The regionalization layer was constructed from the fault lines and channels layers, plus the flooding mask presented in an earlier post. The data are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name in the table to download individual layers.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/support/fault-lines_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;fault-lines_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Fault lines&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/support/rivers-channels_karttur_okaswamps_0_digitized.zip&quot;&gt;rivers-channels_karttur_okaswamps_0_digitized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;River channels&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/geophysiology/geophysiology_wits_okaswamps_1994_pub.zip&quot;&gt;geophysiology_wits_okaswamps_1994_pub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geophysiological regions of the Okavango swmaps&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/support/elev-regions_karttur_okaswamps_0_4demcreate.zip&quot;&gt;elev-regions_karttur_okaswamps_0_4demcreate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation regions&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “NW-drylands” region is intersected by the Panhandle and includes the relict dune-fields west of the Okavango wetlands. The Western side of the Panhandel is uplifted compared to the Eastern side and the relict dunes have heights of approximately 10 meters. These variations where not considered when interpolating the DEM, and consequently the theoretical errors in “NW-drylands” region are comparatively large. The “SW-drylands” is defined as the region South-East of the Thamalakane fault line. It is the most data-poor region and the elevation estimates are poor over some parts of this region. The parallel Kunyere and Thamalakane fault lines define a stair between the Okavango wetlands and the SE-drylands. This stair, or “trappa”, define a third region: “kunyere-trappa”. Finally the Okavango wetlands (the maximum flooding area - see &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post) defines the central region: “oka-wetlands”. This region also include all the channels draining the Okavango swamps across the Linyanti-trappa, and also includes the Boteti River valley. All regions have sections where the boundaries are less pronounced. For sections across sub-regions with no, or less, defined fault lines, nearby elevation points from the adjacent region were included in both regions spanning the boundary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to creating a DEM for the larger Okavango region, we also created three DEMs related to the palaeo-lakes in the Okavango region:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ngami&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mababe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mkgadikgadi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three are situated partly within and partly outside the area of the main map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;north-west-drylands&quot;&gt;North-West drylands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dryland region to the north west (“NW-drylands”) of the Thamalakane/Kunyere fault line (Figure 2), excluding the Okavango swamps and spanning both sides of the Panhandle entry channel, was interpolated using three combined datasets; GPS elevations from the gravity survey, beacon heights drawn from Botswana maps and heights from the Digital Chart of the World (DCW), table 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 3. Elevation point data sources used for interpolating the region &quot;NW-drylands&quot; (see figure 1). All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS surveyed elevations&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonometric beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_dcw_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_dcw_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Digital Chart of World heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;south-east-drylands&quot;&gt;South-East drylands&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The south eastern region (“SE-drylands”), on the uplifted side of the Thamalakane fault and intersected by the Boteti valley, was interpolated using GPS elevations from the gravity survey and beacons identified from Botswana maps, table 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 4. Elevation point data sources used for interpolating the region &quot;SE-drylands&quot; (see figure 2). All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the bottom of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS surveyed elevation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonometric beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kunyere-trappa-region&quot;&gt;Kunyere trappa region&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The region between the Kunyere and Thamalakane fault lines (“kunyere-trappa”) (figure 2) was interpolated separately. The region is intersected by the rivers draining the distal arms of the Okavango swamps before they join the Thamalakane River (defined by the Thamalakane fault line). The “Kunyere-trappa” region was interpolated using GPS elevations from the GPS/gravity survey and trigonometric beacon heights from Botswana maps, table 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 5. Elevation point data sources used for interpolating the region &quot;kunyere-trappa&quot; (see figure 2). All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the bottom of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS surveyed elevation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonometric beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;okavango-wetlands-region&quot;&gt;Okavango wetlands region&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last, central, region is the area of maximum flooding (see &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post) of the Okavango wetlands, “oka-wetlands”. To interpolate this region we used three different data sets; GPS elevations from the gravity survey, beacon heights from Botswana maps and GPS points collected by University of Cape Town (UCT), table 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 6. Elevation point data sources used for interpolating the region &quot;oka-wetlands&quot; (see figure 2). All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum  All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS surveyed elevation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonometric beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-subreg_gps-uct_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-subreg_gps-uct_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;GPS survey by University of Cape Town&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;unused-trigonometric-heights&quot;&gt;Unused trigonometric heights&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all trigonometric beacon heights identified in various Botswana maps were used. For completeness, also the unused elevation points are supplied here, table 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 7. Identified, but unused, trigonometric beacon heights. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/input/elev-pt-unused_beacons_okaswamps_2000_all-regions.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-unused_beacons_okaswamps_2000_all-regions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Unused beacon heights&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okavango-dem&quot;&gt;Okavango DEM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DEM for the larger Okavango region was created by combining the four regional DEMs and then smoothing the compositional DEM across areas with no pronounced faults (see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.2113/1040243&quot;&gt;original article&lt;/a&gt; for details). A few pronounced heights and troughs were added, and the elevation contour lines extracted. The final DEM, as a 500 m raster and as contour lines are listed and available for download in table 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 8. Elevation data layers available for the larger Okavango region. All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layer&lt;/strong&gt; (shape file)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/okaswamps/elev-contours_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-contours_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation contour lines for the larger Okavango area.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/okaswamps/dem_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geo-interpoalted DEM in 500 m spatial resolution&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/okaswamps/dem-sd_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-sd_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Estimated error (1 standard deviation)&lt;br /&gt; of the interpolated DEM&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/okaswamps/dem_karttur_ne-bw_2000_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem_karttur_ne-bw_2000_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geo-interpoalted DEM over NV Botswana&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-okavango-alluvial-fan&quot;&gt;The Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Okavango Alluvial Fan (Figure 3), forms an almost perfectly shaped cone where small variations potentially could reveal sedimentation, erosion or tectonic movements. To compare the interpolated DEM with a theoretical cone, several spatial entities related to the Okavango Alluvial Fan were identified or created, table 9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 9. Spatial data layers associated with the Okavango Alluvial Fan. All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layers&lt;/strong&gt; (shape files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan-apex_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The apex (beginning, point from spreading out)&lt;br /&gt; of the Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The surface area of the Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan-isodist_karttur_okaswamps_0_fromapex&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Iso-distance lines (25 km interval) from the apex&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan-cone-dem_karttur_okasvamps_0_v2001&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Idealized, perfectly cone shaped DEM&lt;br /&gt; over the Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;alluvial-fan-residual-dem_karttur_okasvamps_0_v2001&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation difference between the idealized and&lt;br /&gt; the interpolated DEMs over the Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lake-ngami-region&quot;&gt;Lake Ngami Region&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted above, a special DEM was created for Lake Ngami and its surroundings. The palaeo shorelines of Lake Ngami were omitted from the DEM, that thus shows the base level of these shorelines. Extracting the base levels we could analyse the topography of the shorelines. The results indicate that the palaeo shorelines are tilted towards north-east. All the data for the Lake Ngami DEM analysis are listed in table 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 10. Spatial data layers available for the Lake Ngami Region. All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;p&gt;| Layer name                                                                                                                    | Layer content                                                                                                                                         |
|:——————————————————————————————————————————|:——————————————————————————————————————————————————|
| &lt;strong&gt;Vector layers&lt;/strong&gt; (shape files)                                                                                               |                                                                                                                                                       |
| [centreline_karttur_lakengami_0&lt;em&gt;v2001](../../docs/dem/lakengami/centreline_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.zip)                     | The central axis of Lake Ngami&lt;br /&gt; (for analysing tilting)                                                                                            |
| &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/elev-contours_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-contours_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;               | Elevation contour lines for the Lake Ngami basin, &lt;br /&gt; _disregarding&lt;/em&gt; any ridges (i.e. palaeo-shorelines)&lt;br /&gt; or channels.                            |
| &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt; | Elevation point data (best estimate and error)&lt;br /&gt;  extracted from the generated DEM (GeoTiff)&lt;br /&gt;for the base level of Lake Ngami palaeo-shorelines. |
| &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/elev-pt_beacons_lakengami_0_frommap.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt_beacons_lakengami_0_frommap&lt;/a&gt;                       | Input elevation data from existing beacons,&lt;br /&gt; used for the geo-interolation                                                                         |
| &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/elev-pt_gps_lakengami_1999_grav-survey.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt_gps_lakengami_1999_grav-survey&lt;/a&gt;                 | Input elevation data from a precision&lt;br /&gt;gravity/GPS survey, used for the geo-interolation                                                            |
| &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/isodist_karttur_lakengami_0_centreline.zip&quot;&gt;isodist_karttur_lakengami_0_centreline&lt;/a&gt;                 | Distances along the central axis (see top row)&lt;br /&gt; for defining proximity (tilting) along palaeo-shoreliens                                           |
| &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/palaeo-shore-line_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;palaeo-shore-line_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;       | Lake Ngami palaeo shorlines&lt;br /&gt; interpreted from &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;Landsat image&lt;/a&gt;                                                                     |
| &lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)                                                                                             |                                                                                                                                                       |
| &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/dem_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;                               | Geo-interpoalted DEM in 500 m spatial resolution                                                                                                      |
| &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/dem-sd_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-sd_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;                         | Estimated error (1 standard deviation) of the interpolated DEM                                                                                        |
| &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/lakengami/natcol_lt05_lakengami_199407_byte.tif.zip&quot;&gt;natcol_lt05_lakengami_199407_byte&lt;/a&gt;                       | Natural color Landsat TM image                                                                                                                        |&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;mababe-depression-region&quot;&gt;Mababe Depression Region&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The special DEM for the Mababe depression was done using only the gravity GPS surveyed elevations points. The DEM for the Mababe depression excludes all local ridges, including the palaeo shoreline defining palaeo Lake Mababe. Water channels, including the drainage connecting Mababe Depression with both the Linyanti and Okavango swamps are also excluded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results indicate that the palaeo shorelines are tilted towards south-west, which is exactly opposite the tilting of the shorelines of Lake Ngami. This suggests that the region between the two palaeo-lakes must have sunken since the lakes died out. In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.2113/1040243&quot;&gt;scientific article&lt;/a&gt; we speculate that this depends on sagging due to the shear weight of the sediments deposited over the Okavango Alluvial Fan. All the data for the Mababe depression DEM are listed in table 11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 11. Spatial data layers available for the Mababe Depression Region. All the data layers are projected to SUTM 34 using the WGS84 datum. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layers&lt;/strong&gt; (shape files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/centreline_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;centreline_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The central axis of Mababe Depression&lt;br /&gt; (for analysing tilting)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/elev-contours_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-contours_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation contour lines for the Mababe Depression, &lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;disregarding&lt;/em&gt; any ridges (i.e. palaeo-shorelines)&lt;br /&gt; or channels.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation point data (best estimate and error)&lt;br /&gt;  extracted from the generated DEM (GeoTiff)&lt;br /&gt;for the base level of Mababe Depression palaeo-shorelines.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/elev-pt_gps_mababedepr_1999_grav-survey.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt_gps_mababedepr_1999_grav-survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Input elevation data from a precision&lt;br /&gt;gravity/GPS survey, used for the geo-interolation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/isodist_karttur_mababedepr_0_centreline.zip&quot;&gt;isodist_karttur_mababedepr_0_centreline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Distances along the central axis (see top row)&lt;br /&gt; for defining proximity (tilting) along palaeo-shoreliens&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/palaeo-shore-line_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;palaeo-shore-line_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Mababe Depression palaeo shorlines&lt;br /&gt; interpreted from &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;Landsat image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/dem_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geo-interpoalted DEM in 500 m spatial resolution&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/dem-sd_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-sd_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Estimated error (1 standard deviation) of the interpolated DEM&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mababedepr/natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_byte.tif.zip&quot;&gt;natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_byte&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Natural color Landsat TM image&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mkgadikgadi-ridge-region&quot;&gt;Mkgadikgadi Ridge Region&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The special DEM for the Mkgadikgadi Ridge was done using only the gravity GPS surveyed elevations points. The DEM for the Mkgadikgadi Ridge region excludes all local ridges, including the Mkgadikgadi Ridge (Lake Mkgadikgadi palaeo shoreline) itself. Also water channels, including the drainage along the Boteti River are excluded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results indicate that the palaeo shoreline is not level with the geoid but has a dip that is at its deepest exactly along the central axis of the Okavango Alluvial Fan. This corroborates the hypothesis that sagging has caused the tectonic depressions along the central axis of the Okavango Alluvial Fan, including the Panhandle entry channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When restoring the data in July 2019 (almost 20 years after the work was done), the layer for the estimated DEM confidence level (dem-sd_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_pub.tif) had one row and one column less compared to the interpolated DEM itself (dem_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_pub.tif). I could not find the reason, and the layers available thus differ in size. All the data for the Mkgadikgadi Ridge Region DEM are listed in table 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 12. Spatial data layers available for the Mkgadikgadi Ridge Region. All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layers&lt;/strong&gt; (shape files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/elev-contours_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-contours_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Elevation contour lines for the Makgadikgadi Ridge region, &lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;disregarding&lt;/em&gt; any ridges (i.e. palaeo-shorelines)&lt;br /&gt; or channels.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Elevation point data (best estimate and error)&lt;br /&gt;  extracted from the generated DEM (GeoTiff)&lt;br /&gt;for the base level of Makgadikgadi Ridge (palaeo-shoreline).&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/elev-pt_gps_mkgadiridge_1999_grav-survey.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt_gps_mkgadiridge_1999_grav-survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Input elevation data from a precision&lt;br /&gt;gravity/GPS survey, used for the geo-interolation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/isodist_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_paleoshoreline.zip&quot;&gt;isodist_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_paleoshoreline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Distances along the palaeo shore line&lt;br /&gt; for defining proximity (tilting)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/palaeo-shore-line_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;palaeo-shore-line_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Makgadikgadi palaeo shorlines&lt;br /&gt; interpreted from &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;Landsat image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/dem_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Geo-interpoalted DEM in 500 m spatial resolution&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/dem-sd_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-sd_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Estimated error (1 standard deviation) of the interpolated DEM&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/mkgadiridge/natcol_lt05_mkgadiridge_199407_byte.tif.zip&quot;&gt;natcol_lt05_mkgadiridge_199407_byte&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Natural color Landsat TM image&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okavango-swamps-water-level-dem&quot;&gt;Okavango swamps water level DEM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survey campaigns conducted by University of Cape Town (UCT) during 1994, 1995, 1996 and 1998 also included measurements of the elevation of surface water, table 13. The 1995 campaign was the most extensive. Using sites with overlapping elevations, all the UCT surface water level data were linearly transferred to represent the 1995 situation. The adjusted elevation data was then used for constructing a surface water table DEM for the Okavango wetlands, table 13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 13. Water surface elevation data for the Central parts of the Okavango Swamps.  All layers are available for download towards the end of this post, or you can click the Layer name to download each layer.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector layers&lt;/strong&gt; (shape files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1994_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1994_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Water surface elevation from the UCT 1994 campaign.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1995_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1995_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Water surface elevation from the UCT 1995 campaign.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1996_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1996_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Water surface elevation from the UCT 1996 campaign.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1998_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1998_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Water surface elevation from the UCT 1998 campaign.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster layers&lt;/strong&gt; (GeoTiff files)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/watersurface/dem-water-surface_karttur_okaswamp_1995_v2001.tif.zip&quot;&gt;dem-water-surface_karttur_okaswamp_1995_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;DEM for the Okavango water table&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/dem/support/&quot;&gt;GitHub repo with fault lines, river channels and elevation  regionalizations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/dem/input/&quot;&gt;GitHub repo with Elevation point data used as input for generating DEM&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/dem/okavango/&quot;&gt;GitHub repo with Elevation data covering the greater Okavango region&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/dem/lakengami/&quot;&gt;GitHub repo with Elevation data covering palaeo Lake Ngami&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/dem/mababedepr/&quot;&gt;GitHub repo with Elevation data covering palaeo Lake Mababe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/dem/mkgadiridge/&quot;&gt;GitHub repo with Elevation data covering Mkgadikgadi Ridge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/dem/watersurface/&quot;&gt;GitHub repo with water surface elevation data covering the Okavango wetlands&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/dem/alluvialfan/&quot;&gt;GitHub repo with data related to the Okavango Alluvial Fan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgement&quot;&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work was done as part on an international co-operation within the Okavango Research Group headed by prof. T.S.McCarthy, Department of Geology, Wits University. My post doctoral scholarship was financed by the Swedish Royal Academy of Sciences.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Okavango" /><category term="topography" /><category term="tectonics" /><category term="Earth movements" /><summary type="html">Creating a regional Digital Elevation Model for the Okavango Delta, Botswana</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/avg-trmm-3b43v7-precip_3B43_trmm_2001-2016_A" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ecoregion classification</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-landcover/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ecoregion classification" /><published>2019-07-18T11:27:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-18T11:27:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-landcover</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-landcover/">&lt;p&gt;This post summarizes the ecoregion map over the Okavango Delta, Botswana that I did back in 1999 together with Jenny McCarty (a visiting PhD student from Sweden) and Terence McCarthy (professor at University of the Witwatersrand [Wits] and leader of the Okavango Research Group at Wits). I was at Wits as a post doc sponsored by the Swedish Royal Academy of Sciences. The mapping project was partly done within the SAFARI 2000 evaluation programme of the MODIS sensor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original article &lt;em&gt;Ecoregion classification in the Okavango Delta, Botswana from multitemporal remote sensing&lt;/em&gt; was published in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/01431160500113583&quot;&gt;special issue on SAFARI2000 in the Journal of Remote Sensing&lt;/a&gt;. The article is also found under its &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/01431160500113583&quot;&gt;DOI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ecoregion map is available for download (e.g. as a zipped GeoTiff, or print ready map) towards the end of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Okavango Delta, or wetland in Northern Botswana is one of the world’s largest inland alluvial fans. The Delta is composed of thousands of islands in a matrix of wetlands. The wetland system is partly fed by local summer rains, but more water enters through the Okavango River that drains part of the Angolan Highlands (Figure 1). Annual inflow varies largely, and &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr/&quot;&gt;historical evidence&lt;/a&gt; shows that flow in the past has been both much larger and much smaller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/oka-tiles_wrs2_okaswamps_0_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 1. The Okavango Delta, Botswana; the figure shows the Landsat scenes used for the ecoregion classification and the small inset images also shows the Okavango River Basin.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The upper section of the Okavango wetland is confined to a 10 km wide entry valley – the Panhandle. The Panhandle ends at the apex of the true Delta, where also the Okavango River divides into a series of channels (figure 2). Today, water flows from the apex of the Delta to the Nqoga (East) and Jao (South East) channels, with very little water flowing south towards the Thaoge channel. Early travellers, including Livingstone and the Swedish explorer Andersson, reported Thaoge to be the largest channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/natcol-rivers-topo_okaswamps_199407_ql.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 2. River channels and topography of the Okavango Delta, Botswana. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Panhandle and the upper part of the Delta are flooded with water almost the whole year around, and hence form permanent swamps (figure 3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/flooding-freq_okaswamps_1970-2000_ql.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 3. Flooding frequency of the Okavango Delta, Botswana, 1970-2000. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical species in the permanent swamp include papyrus and reed, but also less dense stands of other aquatic grasses. Further downstream water only inundates this extremely flat terrain when the floods arrive – forming the seasonal swamps. As it takes water four to six months to travel from the Angolan highlands to the Delta, the flooding occurs during the dry winter season (&lt;a href=&quot;https://karttur.github.io/setup-theme-blog/blog/dualmovie/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post contains an animation showing the rainfall and flooding patterns of the Okavango 2000 to 2016). Hence the wetland is at its largest during the driest season, which of course is of tremendous importance for the wildlife and general ecology of the whole region. Different species of aquatic grasses and sedges dominate different areas of the seasonal swamps, depending on flooding frequency, salinity and water depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elevated areas in the flooded regions form islands – if the flooding is less frequent and do not drown the islands they are normally covered by trees (riparian forest). If regularly drowned, grasslands will dominate. The islands are extremely important for regulating the water balance and the salinity of the water, and also for directing flow down the Delta. Evapotranspiration of water from the Delta to the atmosphere is mediated by the vegetation on islands – and hence salt groundwater forms under the islands. This is frequently seen as salt crusts or salt pans on islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Areas that are even further downstream get flooded only during years with heavy rainfall – hence forming occasional swamps (figure 3). Some parts of the Delta have obviously not been flooded for centuries, and dry woodlands and grasslands (including pasture and grazing land) dominate the landscape. Also here the distribution of different tree species, like mopane and acacia, is of importance for the wildlife. In its distal parts the Delta gradually changes into the surrounding Kalahari Desert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The occurrence of different types of wetlands, islands and woodland ecoregions is extremely important for understanding how the Okavango functions. Predicting the patterns of wildlife migrations, predator-prey dynamics, or how water will flow under different climatic scenarios, demands a detailed description of the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;classification-methods-and-materials&quot;&gt;Classification methods and materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ecoregion classification was done using 12 classes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;open water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;permanent wetlands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;primary floodplains&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;secondary floodplains&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;flooded grasslands (wet meadows)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;riparian forests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;occasional flooded grasslands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dry woodlands (dominated by Acacia)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dry woodlands (dominated by Mopane)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dry woodlands (dominated by Combretum)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dry grasslands&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;salt pans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classification was done using both high resolution &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;Landsat images&lt;/a&gt; and moderate to low resolution &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr/&quot;&gt;time series of ATSR, Landsat and NOAA-AVHRR images&lt;/a&gt;. The latter images were only used for determining the flooding pattern (as shown in figure 3). Some of the 12 classes above have identical spectral properties and can not be distinguished in single scenes (e.g. the Landsat images). The categorization between different types of grasslands and pans (i.e. between i) flooded, ii) occasionally flooded or iii) dry) were done using the flooding frequency. Figure 4 illustrates the different ecoregions used in the classification, with the color code bar corresponding to the colors in the ecoregion map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/lc01-water_photo_okaswamps_2000_m.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/lc01-water_photo_okaswamps_2000_s.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/lc02-permswamp_photo_okaswamps_2000_m.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/lc02-permswamp_photo_okaswamps_2000_s.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/lc03-primfloodplain_photo_okaswamps_2000_m.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/lc03-primfloodplain_photo_okaswamps_2000_s.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/lc04-secfloodplain_photo_okaswamps_2000_m.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/lc04-secfloodplain_photo_okaswamps_2000_s.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/lc05-wetmeadow_photo_okaswamps_2000_m.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/lc05-wetmeadow_photo_okaswamps_2000_s.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/lc06-riverineforest_photo_okaswamps_2000_m.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/lc06-riverineforest_photo_okaswamps_2000_s.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/lc07-occasionaflood_photo_okaswamps_2000_m.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/lc07-occasionaflood_photo_okaswamps_2000_s.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/lc08-woodland-acacia_photo_okaswamps_2000_m.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/lc08-woodland-acacia_photo_okaswamps_2000_s.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/lc09-woodland-mopane_photo_okaswamps_2000_m.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/lc09-woodland-mopane_photo_okaswamps_2000_s.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/lc11-grassland-dry_photo_okaswamps_2000_m.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/lc11-grassland-dry_photo_okaswamps_2000_s.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/llc12-saltpan-dry_photo_okaswamps_2000_m.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/lc12-saltpan-dry_photo_okaswamps_2000_s.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 4. Illustration of the ecoregion categories used in the classification.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earth observing satellites have during the last decades become a powerful tool for portraying the earth’s surface. Commercial satellite pictures down to metre resolution are now becoming globally available. Ideally the resolution (or grain size) on a satellite image should correspond with the structures on the ground that are to be identified. Apart from the grain size, also the spectral resolution is important. For identifying and classifying the ecoregions of the Okavango we used &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;Landsat Thematic Mapper (TM) data&lt;/a&gt;. This data has a resolution of 30 metres, and is spectrally resolved into blue, green, red, infrared (three spectral bands) and thermal infrared (temperature). To cover all of Okavango, four images had to be pasted together (figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pasted satellite images with seven spectral bands were used for classifying the Okavango and its surroundings into 12 ecoregions. After many trials and as many errors, we decided on using an approach that combined the spectral information with known logical relations of spatial patterns. The classification procedure started with identifying the “colours” and “temperatures” of different sites that we had visited in the field. Hence we knew the spectral properties (or signals as the jargon goes) of for example water, papyrus, reed, sedges, grassland, riparian forest, salt crust, mopane and acacia woodland, to name a few. Knowing the signals we let the computer look for areas with similar spectral properties and assigned them to the corresponding class. As the Okavango is very large this did not work out that well, and it also turned out that papyrus and reed had very similar spectral properties to trees. This happens because the papyrus and reed is so dense that no water is seen when looked upon from above. Another obvious problem was water inundation in the seasonal swamp, disclosing the dominating vegetation from being detected. These errors could all be resolved by adopting time series of more coarse satellite images. &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr/&quot;&gt;From 1 km resolution images we derived a general flooding pattern.&lt;/a&gt; Hence we could say that papyrus identified outside the permanently flooded region was erroneous, and probably should be classified as dry woodland instead. And vice versa. We could also distinguish between permanent and seasonal swamps, even if the inundation in the Landsat TM data prevented us from “seeing” below the water-surface present at the particular time that image was acquired. We also encountered a lot of problems with classifying small-scale structures in the Delta itself. Many islands are only around 30 x 30 metres, or one picture element (pixel) in size. And as mentioned, differentiating between papyrus and trees was difficult. However, the occurrence of a salt pan or salt crust indicates that the likelihood of a nearby trees is high. (The trees transpirate more, and hence give rise to saline ground water). It is also unlikely that papyrus or reed grow very far from a channel, or in the middle of an island. This kind of small scale, neighborhood information was used for improving the classification accuracy in the permanent and seasonal swamp regions. The final classification was hence based on more than 50 data sources, including the seven Landsat bands, the initial classification, degree of membership for each pixel with different signals, neighborhood properties, flooding frequencies, and many more. This information was combined in an expert system of the type “If ….. then ….. else ….”. An expert rule for papyrus could hence look something like “If classified as papyrus or tree, and permanently flooded, and close to channel, and far from salt crust, and surrounded by other wetland classes then papyrus else ….”. Figure 5 summarizes the methodological approach&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;../../images/method-flow-chart_karttur_oka-ecoregions_0_0.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/method-flow-chart_karttur_oka-ecoregions_0_0.png&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 5. Schematic summary of methodological approach applied for mapping the ecoregions of the Okavango wetlands.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final map contains 12 ecoregions. This map was simplified into versions with 11 and 6 classes respectively for improved readability and also for improved accuracy. The map in six classes is accurate to 75 %, whereas the 12-class map is accurate to 63 %. Around half the errors is dependent on generalisations in the data, and on small scale (up to approximately 200 metres) inaccuracies in the geometry of the satellite images compared to the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;full-resolution-geotiff-layer&quot;&gt;Full resolution GeoTiff layer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full resolution (28.5 m resolution) ecoregion classification is available as a GeoTiff image. The downloadable GeoTiff is projected to UTM34S (EPSG:32734), and available as a &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/landcover/landcover_lt05_okaswamps_1994_pub.tif.zip&quot;&gt;zip file&lt;/a&gt;. Note, that the data has been reprojected to the standard UTM projection using WGS84, not the Cape datum as in the original study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/landcover_lt05_okaswamps_1994_ql.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Ecoregion classification over the Okavango wetlands, Botswana. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;print-ready-small-a4-map&quot;&gt;Print ready small (A4) map&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;../../images/landcover_lt05_okaswamps_1994_map.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/landcover_lt05_okaswamps_1994_map-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Print ready map of the ecoregion classification layer over the Okavango wetlands, Botswana. Slide the mouse over the image, right click and select &quot;Save Link As&quot; or click on the map to get a pop-up image that you can drag to your desktop. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;print-ready-large-a0-poster-map&quot;&gt;print ready large (A0) poster map&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://karttur.github.io/common/images/oka-landcover-poster_wits_joburg_2000_ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Print ready A0 poster map of the ecoregion classification layer over the Okavango wetlands, Botswana. Use the link below to get to the page where you can download the full resolution poster.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full resolution poster is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://karttur.github.io/professional/poster/poster-oka-landcover_2000_tg/index.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/landcover&quot;&gt;GitHub folder with GeoTiff of ecoregion classification&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgement&quot;&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classification work was done as part on an international co-operation within the Okavango Research Group headed by prof. T.S.McCarthy, Department of Geology, Wits University. Financing came through a scholarship from the The Swedish Foundation for International Cooperation in Research and Higher Education for doctoral student Jenny McCarthy and as a post doctoral scholarship financed by the Swedish Royal Academy of Sciences, for the author.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Okavango" /><category term="Landsat" /><category term="landcover classification" /><category term="Expert system" /><summary type="html">Ecoregion classification of the Okavango Delta, Botswana</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/avg-trmm-3b43v7-precip_3B43_trmm_2001-2016_A" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Geophysiological regions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-geophysiology/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Geophysiological regions" /><published>2019-07-17T11:27:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-17T11:27:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-geophysiology</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-geophysiology/">&lt;p&gt;The Okavango Swamps in Botswana (figure 1) are composed of a mosaic of islands and wetlands with a pronounced annual inundation cycle (see &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr/&quot;&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; post). The Panhandle entry valley (see figure 1) is mostly permanently inundated, and so is the proximal region of the swamps as the water leaves the Panhandle and spreads out over the alluvial fan (usually referred to as a “delta” but that is strictly speaking not correct). Further downstream the permanent wetlands give way to floodplains and then to grasslands with regular or occasional (during wetter years only) flooding. Salt pans occur both in the lower reaches of the alluvial fan and on islands. Island rims are usually elevated with riparian forests. Outside the region that is flooded the Kalahari desert with its sparse woodlands take over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent my Post Doc time (1999-2001) at University of the Witwatersrand (Johannesburg, South Africa) studying the Okavango swamps. My first results led me to construct a regionalization of patterns and process (henceforth: geophysiology) of the swamps. The initial results were presented at the &lt;em&gt;28th International conference on remote sensing of the environment.&lt;/em&gt; Cape Town, 27-31 March 2000, in the article &lt;a href=&quot;https://karttur.github.io/common/pdf/oka_RSENV-CD_capetown_2000_tg-etal.pdf&quot;&gt;Portraying the geophysiology of the Okavango Delta, Botswana&lt;/a&gt;. In this post I briefly describe the regionalization and provide the link for downloading the regions as a geospatial data layer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;okavango-geophysiolgical-regions&quot;&gt;Okavango geophysiolgical regions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Okavango Delta is divided into four distinct geophysiological regions; the Panhandle - a transitory entry valley confined to a tectonic graben, the permanent swamps, the seasonal swamps, and the region with flooding only during wet years (“occassional swamps”) (table 1 and figure 1). Water level in the Panhandle and on the floodplains of the seasonal swamps vary up to 2 meters annually, whereas the permanent swamps have a less varied water level. Both the swamp geophysiology and the island types vary from region to region, table 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;

Table 1. Geophysiological regions of the Okavango delta
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geophysiological region&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Dominating wetland types&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Typical island/dryland types&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Panhandle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;meandering channels,&lt;br /&gt;lakes, reed swamps&lt;br /&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Papyrus, Phragmites&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;sand banks, grasslands&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Permanent swamp&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;channels, lakes, reed swamps&lt;br /&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Papyrus, Phragmites, Miscanthus&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;scrollbar &amp;amp; anthill islands&lt;br /&gt; salt pans (island interiors)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seasonal swamp&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;channels, floodplains&lt;br /&gt;(sedges and grasses)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;inverted channel islands,&lt;br /&gt; anthill islands, saltpan islands&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Occasional flooded area&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;flooded grasslands (wet meadows), salt pans&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;grasses and sedges&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dryland&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Savannah, dry forest&lt;br /&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Acacia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Combretum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mopane&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a combination of &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr/&quot;&gt;coarse resolution satellite image time series of flooding&lt;/a&gt; and a high resolution &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;Landsat composite&lt;/a&gt;, we converted the Geophysiological regions in table 1 to spatial extents, figure 1. These regions were later used in several subsequent studies, including for &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landcover/&quot;&gt;ecoregion classification&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spatially defined geophysiological regions are available as a shape file in geographic coordinates (longitude and latitude) &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/geophysiology/geophysiology_wits_okaswamps_1994_pub.zip&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/geophysiology_wits_okaswamps_1994_m.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 1. Geophysiological regions of the Okavango swamps, Botswana.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/geophysiology/&quot;&gt;GitHub folder with the geophysiological data (shape files)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Okavango" /><category term="Geophysiological regions" /><summary type="html">Geophysiological regions of the Okavango swammps, Botswana; maps and concepts developed during my postdoc period at University of the Witwatersrand in South Africa.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/avg-trmm-3b43v7-precip_3B43_trmm_2001-2016_A" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Flooding from AVHRR, ATSR and Landsat quicklook images</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-avhrr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flooding from AVHRR, ATSR and Landsat quicklook images" /><published>2019-07-16T11:27:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-16T11:27:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-avhrr</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-avhrr/">&lt;p&gt;Understanding the Okavango swamps in Botswana requires knowledge on both the seasonal and inter-annual variations in inundation (flooding). During my Post Doc period (1999-2001) at University of the Witwatersrand in Johannesburg, South Africa, we acquired a series of different coarse resolution image data sets, including from several generations of the Advanced Very High Resolution Radiometer (AVHRR) operated by the US National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), the European Space Agency (ESA) Along Track Scanning Radiometer (ATSR), and low resolution (quicklook) Landsat images. As noted in the &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; post, this was before the release of free Landsat images and we used the quicklooks available on internet (intended for “window shopping”). Primarily these datasets were used for mapping the flooding dynamics of the Okavango swamps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details on the methods for processing the data presented (and made available for download) are available in a scientific article published in the journal Ambio:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1579/0044-7447-32.7.453&quot;&gt;McCarthy, J., Gumbricht, T., McCarthy, T. Frost, P. Wessels, K. &amp;amp; Seidel, K., 2003. &lt;strong&gt;Flooding Patterns of the Okavango Wetland in Botswana between 1972 and 2000.&lt;/strong&gt; AMBIO: A Journal of the Human Environment, 32 (7) , 453-457.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-earliest-image-and-the-largest-flood&quot;&gt;The earliest image and the largest flood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The largest flood I have found occurred in 1963. This is a decade before the first Landsat satellite was put into orbit, but the flood was captured by a Corona (US spy) satellite. Figure 1 shows the full Corona image, along side a flood mask that I created from the image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/corona-text_1963_09_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask_corona_1963_09_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1. Corona spy satellite image over the Okavango Delta, Botswana acquired 2 September 1963; the right panel shows the inundated area interpreted from the Corona image.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;avhrr&quot;&gt;AVHRR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had two different sources of AVHRR images. Via the USAid Famine Early Warning System (FEWS) 10-day composites of AVHRR data over the whole of Africa were freely available for 1992, 1993 and 1995. And then the South African Institute for Soil, Climate and Water had stored AVHRR images over southern Africa starting in 1985. The latter were the main source of the data in the Ambio article; other data sources could almost be seen as supplementary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;avhrr-1985-2000&quot;&gt;AVHRR 1985-2000&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total we got access to 2951 AVHRR scenes from the Institute for Soil, Climate and Water for the period 1985 to 2000. In a first step we reprojected these to SUTM 34 and masked out all clouds. If you are interested in these images, please drop me an email. They are copyright protected, and I can not share them freely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the 2951 scenes we selected the best 381 and applied a clustering classification with manual selection of flooded areas (see figure 7 for a summary of the method). A three-dimensional contextual and weighted filter – using the preceding and following images as the third dimension, smoothed the initial water classification. Pixel locations with clouds were handled by seeking the closest cloud-free image for that pixel.
 In total we created complete flooding maps for 373 dates. The GeoTiff files for these dates are available for download &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/flooding/floodmask_daily-compositions_avhrr_okaswamps.zip&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the set of 373 images of composed dates we estimated the flooding for 152 months between February 1985 and December 2000. The monthly GeoTiff layers at 1 km spatial resolution are available for download in two versions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/flooding/floodmask_avhrr_oka-only_1985-2000_monthly.zip&quot;&gt;Okavango swamps only&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/flooding/floodmask_avhrr_oka-ngami-linyanti_1985-2000_monthly.zip&quot;&gt;Including Linyanti and Lake Ngami&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the latter the three months of July, August and September 1993 are missing. The images are boolean masks indicating flooding / non-flooding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;monthly-inundation-pattern&quot;&gt;Monthly inundation pattern&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2 shows the monthly flooding frequencies for the period 1985-2000 based on the monthly images. The monthly frequency GeoTiff layers representing 1985 to 2000 at 1 km spatial resolution are downloadable &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/flooding/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000_monthly.zip&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The images are in byte format with the cell value denoting % of time inundated. The frequency images only show the Okavango; Linyanti and Lake Ngami are masked out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000@M01_oka-only.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000@M02_oka-only.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000@M03_oka-only.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000@M04_oka-only.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000@M05_oka-only.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000@M06_oka-only.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000@M07_oka-only.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000@M08_oka-only.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000@M09_oka-only.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000@M10_oka-only.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000@M11_oka-only.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000@M12_oka-only.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 2. Monthly flooding frequencies 1985-2000 for the Okavango wetlands, Botswana. Darkest blue represents 100% flooding frequency. The first row represents January, February and March, etc.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;overall-flooding-frequency&quot;&gt;Overall flooding frequency&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 3 shows the overall flooding frequency for 1985-2000. The GeoTiff layer at 1 km spatial resolution is downloadable &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/flooding/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000_oka-only.tif.zip&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The image is in byte format with the cell value denoting % of time inundated. The image only shows the Okavango; Linyanti and Lake Ngami are masked out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 3. Flooding frequency in the Okavango swamps, Botswana, 1985 to 2000. Image created from time-series of AVHRR satellite images.  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;avhrr-1992-1993-and-1995&quot;&gt;AVHRR 1992, 1993 and 1995&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a long period with relatively larger floods 1960 to 1990 (see figures 1,2 and 5), the early 1990s saw smaller floods in the Okavango. The AVHRR 1992 to 1995 data made available by FEWS (see above) thus show comparatively smaller floods, figure 4. The GeoTiff layers at 1 km spatial resolution are downloadable &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/flooding/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_annual_fews.zip&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The images are in byte format with the cell value denoting % of time inundated. These images were the first set we got access to and were only used in initial studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1992_fews.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1992_fews-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

   &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1993_fews.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1993_fews-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

   &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1995_fews.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1995_fews-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

   &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 4. Annual flooding frequencies 1992,1993 and 1995 for the Okavango wetlands, Botswana. Darkest blue represents 100% flooding frequency. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;landsat-quicklooks&quot;&gt;Landsat quicklooks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the USGS online archive of available Landsat scenes back in 2000, we grabbed all the quicklooks we could find (totaling 92). Using an automatic clustering routine followed by manual selection of water classes we created water masks for each individual scene (see figure 7). The water masks for all 92 scenes can be downloaded as GeoTiff layers &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/flooding/floodmask-scenes_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1972-2000_oka-only.zip&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covering the whole of the Okavango Swamps from Landsat data requires four (4) Landsat scenes (see &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; post). For months with complete (or almost complete) coverage over the Okavango, we created monthly inundation masks. Combining all data for an annual cycle we also created images of the maximum annual flood for years with sufficient data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;monthly-floodmasks&quot;&gt;Monthly floodmasks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 5 shows all the complete monthly composite flood masks that we could create from Landsat quicklooks images. The earliest mask is from November 1972. The GeoTiff data are available for download &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/flooding/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1972-2000_oka-only.zip&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_197211_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_197211_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_197508_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_197508_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_197905_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_197905_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_198405_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_198405_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_198406_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_198406_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_198407_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_198407_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_198408_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_198408_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_199407_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_199407_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_199910_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_199910_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_200004_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_200004_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_200006_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_200006_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_200009_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask_landsat-ql_okaswamps_200009_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

   &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 5. Flood masks over the Okavango Swamps, Botswana, constructed from mosaics of Landsat quicklook images.  The date for each composite is indicated in the image. To view larger version click on one of the images flip by clicking the navigation arrow that appears.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;annual-max-floods&quot;&gt;Annual max floods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual maximum extent (accumulated) of the inundation area made use of all available Landsat quicklooks, figure 6. (Not only the composites shown in figure 5 where used to construct the maps in figure 6). The GeoTiff data for the annual maximum flood are available for download &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/flooding/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1972-2000_oka-only.zip&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1972_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1972_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1975_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1975_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1979_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1979_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1984_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1984_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1985_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1985_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1994_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1994_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1999_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_1999_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

     &lt;a href=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_2000_oka-only.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodmask-max-a_landsat-ql_okaswamps_2000_oka-ql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

   &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 6. Flood masks of accumulated annual max  extent for the Okavango Swamps, Botswana. The data were derived by interpretation of Landsat quicklook images.  The year for each composite is indicated in the image. To view larger version click on one of the images flip by clicking the navigation arrow that appears.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;atsr&quot;&gt;ATSR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 1999 and 2000 we acquired 28 ATSR scenes over the Okavango, you can download the raw scenes cut to the Okavango and projected to SUTM 34 at 1 km spatial resolution &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/flooding/ATSR_rawscenes_okaswamps.zip&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Note that some of the scenes are taken at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ATSR data are of higher quality compared to both Landsat quicklooks and the archived AVHRR data we had access to. We hence used the ATSR for accuracy evaluation of the flood masks created from AVHRR data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extraction of inundated areas from the ATSR images followed the same methods as applied to the AVHRR and Landsat quicklooks; from an initial clustering the clusters representing flooding were manually selected and extracted. Figure 7 illustrates the work flow for generating all the flood masks presented here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/ATSR_raw_19990921_pub.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/ATSR_cluster_19990921_pub.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/ATSR_floodmask_19990921_pub.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 7. Illustration of methods used for creating the boolean flood masks, the left panel shows the original image (ATSR scene shown as false color composite), the middle panel the result of an automatic clustering classification, and the right panel the flood mask derived by manually identifying clusters representing flooded areas (from mid panel image). &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accuracy-evaluation&quot;&gt;Accuracy evaluation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total, the accuracy of the flood masks were tested comparing 12 dates. For each of these 12 dates we created flood masks from data representing two different sensors, either AVHRR versus ATSR, or AVHRR versus Landsat. For most of the dates we had to combine data from adjacent dates to create complete and cloud free maps from both sensors. See the &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1579/0044-7447-32.7.453&quot;&gt;article in Ambio&lt;/a&gt; for details. The cross correlations indicated an agreement of 89% when comparing the flooding masks from different sensors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results for all compared dates are shown in Figure 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third&quot;&gt;
     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/crosstab_avhrr_okaswamps_19940705_landsat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/crosstab_avhrr_okaswamps_19941204_landsat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/crosstab_avhrr_okaswamps_19950215_landsat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/crosstab_avhrr_okaswamps_19990825_atsr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/crosstab_avhrr_okaswamps_19990903_atsr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/crosstab_avhrr_okaswamps_19990905_atsr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/crosstab_avhrr_okaswamps_19990919_atsr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/crosstab_avhrr_okaswamps_19990928_atsr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/crosstab_avhrr_okaswamps_19991007_landsat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/crosstab_avhrr_okaswamps_19991216_atsr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/crosstab_avhrr_okaswamps_20000407_landsat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

     &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/crosstab_avhrr_okaswamps_20000908_landsat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;

   &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 8. Comparison of flood masks for dates with multiple data sources available. Blue indicates that the flood masks from the compared sensors agree; purple and orange that they do not. Source data and dates are given in each map.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cross correlation maps above are available for download as GeoTiff files &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/flooding/floodmasks_cross-correlations_okaswamps.zip&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Note that the data used in the correlations have been massaged to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have the same projection and resolution,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;completely cover the Okavango, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;only show the Okavango swamps, excluding Linyanti swamps and Lake Ngami.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flood-frequency-at-high-spatial-resolution&quot;&gt;Flood frequency at high spatial resolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the mapping and modeling that I wanted to do for the Okavango I needed a higher resolution flood frequency map compared to the 500 m to 1 km spatial resolution of the AVHRR and Landsat quicklooks. To achieve that I combined the flood frequency maps above with the high resolution &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landsat/&quot;&gt;Landsat scenes&lt;/a&gt; that we had received from Anglo American. I then also digitized the river channels in the Okavango swamps and added data on the average flow and flow duration that I got access to. Combining all these sources I then constructed a flood frequency map at 28.5 m spatial resolution, exactly fitting the Landsat composition over the entire Okavango Delta. These two data sources were then the key resources for creating the &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-landcover/&quot;&gt;ecoregion map of the Okavango Delta, the subject of another post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full (28.5) resolution flood frequency map over the Okavango is available as a compressed GeoTiff &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/flooding/floodfreq_multisource_okaswamps_1992-2000_28m.tif.zip&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The map is projected to SUTM 34, and fits exactly with the Landsat composition and the land cover classification, each presented in other posts. Rather than cleaning the high resolution dataset I kept the suspected overestimations outside the actually swamp area. In the subsequent processing I masked out wetlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/floodfreq_multisource_okaswamps_1992-2000_m.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Composite natural color map over the Okavango wetlands, Botswana. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;studies-using-the-flood-data&quot;&gt;Studies using the flood data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flooding data presented in this post were used as input in several other studies. I hope to present these studies in some detail on this blog, in the meantime I supply this list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1579/0044-7447-32.7.453&quot;&gt;McCarthy, J., Gumbricht, T., McCarthy, T. Frost, P. Wessels, K. &amp;amp; Seidel, K., 2003. Flooding Patterns of the Okavango Wetland in Botswana between 1972 and 2000. AMBIO: A Journal of the Human Environment, 32 (7) , 453-457.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1029/2005WR004234&quot;&gt;Bauer, P., Gumbricht, T., &amp;amp; Kinzelbach, W., 2006. A regional coupled surface water/groundwater model of the Okavango Delta, Botswana Water Resources Research, 42 (4) , 1-15.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhydrol.2006.04.040&quot;&gt;Wolski, P., Savenije, H.H.G., Murray-Hudson, M &amp;amp; Gumbricht, T., 2006. Modelling of the flooding in the Okavango Delta, Botswana, using a hybrid reservoir-GIS model. Journal of Hydrology, 331 (1-2) , 58–72.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1080/01431160500113583&quot;&gt;McCarthy, J., Gumbricht, T., &amp;amp; McCarthy, T. S., 2005. Ecoregion classification in the Okavango Delta, Botswana from multitemporal remote sensing. Int J Remote Sensing, 26 (19) , 4339–4357.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhydrol.2003.11.010&quot;&gt;Gumbricht, T., Wolski, P., Frost, P. &amp;amp; McCarthy, T.S., 2004. Forecasting the spatial extent of the annual flood in the Okavango delta, Botswana. Journal of Hydrology, 290 (3-4) , 178–191.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/flooding&quot;&gt;GitHub folder with all flooding data (GeoTiff)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Okavango" /><category term="Landsat quicklooks" /><category term="AVHRR" /><category term="ATSR" /><category term="flooding" /><summary type="html">AVHRR, ATSR and Landsat low resolution image data used for creating the Okavango flooding maps during my postdoc period at University of the Witwatersrand in South Africa.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/avg-trmm-3b43v7-precip_3B43_trmm_2001-2016_A" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Landsat satellite image data</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-landsat/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Landsat satellite image data" /><published>2019-07-15T11:27:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-15T11:27:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-landsat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/oka-landsat/">&lt;style&gt;
table {
    width:30%;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I briefly discuss the Landsat satellite image data I used when studying the Okavango Delta, Botswana, as a postdoc with University of the Witwatersrand (Johannesburg, South Africa) 1999 to 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;landsat-images&quot;&gt;Landsat images&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of my postdoc, Landsat images were not available for free but carried a rather hefty price tag. (The free and open data policy for Landsat images came into force in 2008). We could not afford to purchase any images. Through contacts with Anglo American my supervisor, Professor T.S. McCarthy, got a set of cloud free Landsat Thematic Mapper (TM) images that covered the Okavango, table 1 and figure 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt; Table 1. Landsat scenes used for my postdoc studies on the Okavango swamps, Botswana. &lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Scene&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acquisition date&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;p174r073&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;19940801&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;p174r074&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;19940801&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;p175r073&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;19940701&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;p175r074&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;19890707&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/oka-tiles_wrs2_okaswamps_0_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 1. Landsat scenes used for my postdoc studies on the Okavango swamps, Botswana. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;geometric-precision&quot;&gt;Geometric precision&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we started the projects on the Okavango in 1999, the signals from the Global Positioning System (GPS) were purposefully degraded and had an accuracy of around 100 m. The Landsat data that we used thus had rather large geometric errors. The theoretical geometric error compared to orthorectified aerial photo maps were estimated to about 50 m. The orthorectified photos, however, were also not correct inside the vast Okavango wetlands. As several studies used the four Landsat scenes shown in the figure above, all maps resulting from these studies are plagued by (the same) geometric errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-pleasing-landsat-composite&quot;&gt;The pleasing Landsat composite&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Okavango project, I created a natural color composite of the 4 Landsat scenes listed above. This “pleasing” map was then used as backdrop for many publications highlighting different structures and phenomena in and around the Okavango.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pleasing Landsat composite is available as a single band (paletted) GeoTiff image. The downloadable GeoTiff is projected to UTM34S (EPSG:32734), and available as a &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/pleasing/natcol_lt05_okaswamps_199407_byte.tif.zip&quot;&gt;zip file&lt;/a&gt;. Note, that the data has been reprojected to the standard UTM projection using WGS84, not the Cape datum as in the original study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/natcol_lt05_okaswamps_199407_ql.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Composite natural color map over the Okavango wetlands, Botswana. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/pleasing&quot;&gt;GitHub folder with Natural color (“pleasing”) Landsat composite over the Okavango Swamps&lt;/a&gt;. The image is a zipped GeoTiff at 28.5 m spatial resolution and projected to UTM 34 south (EPSG:32734). It is in byte format and created from a dithered red-green-blue (RGB) composite that in turn was constructed using a Brovey transformation and the four Landsat TM scenes listed above.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Okavango" /><category term="Landsat TM" /><category term="pleasing" /><summary type="html">Landsat satellite image data that was used for creating the Okavango maps during my postdoc period at University of the Witwatersrand in South Africa.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/avg-trmm-3b43v7-precip_3B43_trmm_2001-2016_A" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Okavango spatial data organization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/oka-datafix/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Okavango spatial data organization" /><published>2019-07-13T11:27:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-13T11:27:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/oka-datafix</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/oka-datafix/">&lt;p&gt;This post is mainly for myself, in case I ever need to retrieve the original data from my Post-Doc period again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;landsat-scenes&quot;&gt;Landsat scenes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is restricted to the four landsat scenes that we got from Anglo American, Figure 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt; Table 1. Landsat scenes used for my postdoc studies on the Okavango swamps, Botswana. &lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Scene&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acquisition date&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;p174r073&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;19940801&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;p174r074&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;19940801&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;p175r073&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;19940701&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;p175r074&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;19890707&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../images/oka-tiles_wrs2_okaswamps_0_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Figure 1. Landsat scenes used for my postdoc studies on the Okavango swamps, Botswana. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;geometric-precision&quot;&gt;Geometric precision&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we started the projects on the Okavango in 1999, the signals from the Global Positioning System (GPS) were purposefully degraded and had an accuracy of around 100 m. The Landsat data that we used thus had rather large geometric errors. theoretical geometric error compared to orthorectified aerial photo maps were estimated to about 50 m. The orthorectified photos, however, were also not correct inside the vast Okavango wetlands. As several studies used the four Landsat scenes shown in the figure above, all maps resulting from these studies are plagued by (the same) geometric errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;original-data&quot;&gt;Original data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original landsat scenes are not yet retrieved&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;natural-color-composite&quot;&gt;Natural color composite&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural color (pleasing) composite created using the ERmapper “pleasing.alg” algorithm, exists in many duplicated. But almost all are in reduced (36 m) spatial resolution. However, the original, at 28.5 m did exists as an &lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;.ers&lt;/span&gt;. The script below fixes the &lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;.ers&lt;/span&gt; pleasing image data. Note that I manually edited the nodata to get rid of some stupid wholes in the original version. This means that the 2019 updated version is better compared to the original. Shell script for fixing it with GDAL and ImageMagick:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#Original pleasing image at 28 m
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -overwrite -tr 28.5 28.5 -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/tgdata/mjtrans/ICRAF_timemachine/Users/thomasgumbricht/tempwork/okacd/one/pleasing_delta_LARGE.ers temp.tif

#Translate to fit the landcover map (the new standard extension)
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate -a_ullr 580276.5443080846453086 7988350.1142306961119175 869808.0443080846453086 7718768.6142306961119175 temp.tif natcol_lt05_okaswamps_199407_rgb-bands.tif

#Use ImageMagick to quantisize to 256 colors
convert natcol_lt05_okaswamps_199407_rgb-bands.tif +dither  -colors 255  natcol_lt05_okaswamps_199407_byte.png

#Convert to tiff
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate -a_srs EPSG:32734 -a_ullr 580276.5443080846453086 7988350.1142306961119175 869808.0443080846453086 7718768.6142306961119175 natcol_lt05_okaswamps_199407_byte.png natcol_lt05_okaswamps_199407_byte.tif
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The layer &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/pleasing&quot;&gt;available for download on karttur´s GithHub pages&lt;/a&gt; is the quantisized (byte range, single band) version (natcol_lt05_okaswamps_199407_byte.tif).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;avhrr-dataset&quot;&gt;AVHRR dataset&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had two different sources of AVHRR images. Via the USAid Famine Early Warning System (FEWS) 10-day composites of AVHRR data over the whole of Africa were freely available for 1992, 1993 and 1995. And then the South African Institute for Soil, Climate and Water had stored AVHRR images over southern Africa starting in 1985.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;avhrr-1985-2000&quot;&gt;AVHRR 1985-2000&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total we got access to 2951 AVHRR scenes from the Institute for Soil, Climate and Water for the period 1985 to 2000. In a first step we reprojected these to SUTM 34 and masked out all clouds. From the 2951 scenes we selected the best 381 and applied a clustering classification with manual selection of flooded areas (see figure 7 for a summary of the method). A three-dimensional contextual and weighted filter – using the preceding and following images as the third dimension, smoothed the initial water classification. Pixel locations with clouds were handled by seeking the closest cloud-free image for that pixel. In total we created complete flooding maps for 373 dates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;orignal-dataset&quot;&gt;Orignal dataset&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original dataset, as we got it from the South African Institute for Soil, Climate and Water are available under “./old_CDs/okavango/AVHRR_flood/original”. All 2951 scenes were cloudmasked and saved in Ermapper formats. These can be imported using the python function &lt;em&gt;ImportErsHeadersAVHRRraw&lt;/em&gt;. These files are not available on Karttur´s GitHub pages. The shell script that converts all the images to GeoTiff is called &lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;avhrr_import_raw.sh&lt;/span&gt;, it is &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/scripts/avhrr_import_raw.sh&quot;&gt;available on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;selected-10-day-composites&quot;&gt;Selected 10-day composites&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 373 dates with complete flood mask coverage are available under ‘./old_CDs/okavango/AVHRR_flood/flood/’, and can be imported by running the python function &lt;em&gt;CreateErsHeadersAVHRRf3DailyComp&lt;/em&gt;. These images are &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/flooding/floodmask_daily-compositions_avhrr_okaswamps.zip&quot;&gt;available on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. The shell script that converts all the images to GeoTiff is called &lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;avhrr_import_raw.sh&lt;/span&gt;, it is &lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/scripts/avhrr-f3-daily_flooding-fix.sh&quot;&gt;available on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Note that the script requires a template file for the &lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;ers&lt;/span&gt; to be created for each image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;monthly-floodmasks&quot;&gt;Monthly floodmasks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 373 dates were combined and resampled to represent monthly flood masks. This was done in two version, one including all flooding within the larger Okavango region (also including Lake Nagami and Linyanti swamps), and one version only identifying flooding inside a mask of the Okavango.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The monthly images including Lake Ngami and Linyanti are available under “./old_CDs/okavango/VAIO/Data_spatial/flood/Monthly_byteimages_Linynti_Ngami”. And the images masked to only include the Okavango swamps are under “./old_CDs/okavango/VAIO/Data_spatial/flood/Monthly_Byteimages”. To create the shell script for importing al of them run the python function &lt;em&gt;CreateErsHeadersMonthly&lt;/em&gt;. Both sets of images are available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/flooding&quot;&gt;Karttur’s Github repository&lt;/a&gt;. The script files are called &lt;strong&gt;avhrr_monthly-flooding-oka-only.sh&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;CreateErsHeadersMonthlyOkaLinyantiNgami.sh&lt;/strong&gt; and also available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/scripts&quot;&gt;Karttur’s Github repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;monthly-flood-frequencies&quot;&gt;Monthly flood frequencies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the period 1985 to 2000, the flooding frequencies for each month (January to December) were calculated. The image data is available under ‘./old_CDs/okavango/VAIO/Data_spatial/flood/ERMapper/’. The python function &lt;em&gt;ImportErsHeadersAVHRRmonthlyfreq&lt;/em&gt; creates the shell script file (&lt;strong&gt;avhrr_flooding-freq-month-import.sh&lt;/strong&gt;) for importing these images. The images are available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/flooding&quot;&gt;Karttur’s GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conversion of the data layers to graphical figures with colors and text are done by two stand-alone python functions &lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;IMFloodGraphicsAVHRR_okaonly.sh&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;IMFloodGraphicsAVHRR_oka_linyanti_ngami.sh&lt;/span&gt;. These images are shown in post on &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr/&quot;&gt;AVHRR, ATSR and Landsat quicklook images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1985-2000-overall-flooding-frequency&quot;&gt;1985-2000 overall flooding frequency&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall flooding frequency 19985 to 2000 is imported using GDAL, and then ImageMagick is used for creating a quicklook for the blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#Import overall flooding frequency as GeoTif
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate -a_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/tgdata/old_CDs/okavango/VAIO/Data_spatial/flood/RawData/Frequency/oka_delta_flooding_frequency_%_1985_to_2000.img.ers floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000_0.tif
#Create a jpg quicklook for the blog
convert oka-pleasing_bg_AVHRR_1km.png \( -fuzz 5% -transparent white /Volumes/tgdata/old_CDs/okavango/VAIO/Data_spatial/flood/Monthly_average_graphics/oka_delta_flooding_frequency_%_1985_to_2000.bmp -alpha set -channel A -evaluate set 50% \) -gravity center -flatten temp.png
convert -crop 281x271+24+11 temp.png floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000_0.png
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ImageMagick script for creating the image of overall flooding frequency in the blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;convert -crop 281x271+24+11 temp.png  -pointsize 12 -font Trebuchet -fill 'RGBA(0,10,200,1)' -gravity north -annotate -30+20 'Okavango Delta, Botswana' -gravity south -annotate +30+60 'Flooding frequency from AVHRR images' -annotate +30+45 '1985-2000' \( -size 303x300 xc:none -font Trebuchet -pointsize 45 -gravity center -draw &quot;fill rgba(120,120,120,0.20) text 2,2 'KARTTUR' fill rgba(225,225,225,0.20) text -2,-2 'KARTTUR' fill grey text 0,0 'KARTTUR' &quot; -transparent grey -fuzz 90% \) -composite -quality 80 floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1985-2000_0.jpg
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fews-avhrr-1992-1993-and-1995&quot;&gt;FEWS AVHRR 1992, 1993 and 1995&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FEWS AVHRR data were only used for the initial studies, developing the concepts. Only the annual frequencies could be found, and are imported using a shell script, including the creation of blog ready quicklooks using ImageMagick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -overwrite  -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/tgdata/old_CDs/okavango/delta/HYDRO/h2o_1992_noaa temp.tif
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate -srcwin 0 0 606 600 -a_ullr 556750.0 8000000.0 859750.0 7700000.0 temp.tif floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1992_fews.tif

/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1992_fews.vrt temp.tif
convert oka-pleasing_bg_landsat_500m.png \( temp.tif -alpha set -channel A -evaluate set 60% \) -gravity center -flatten temp.png
convert -crop 562x542+48+22 temp.png floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1992_fews.png
convert floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1992_fews.png -pointsize 24 -font Trebuchet -fill 'RGBA(0,10,200,1)' -gravity north -annotate -50+25 'Okavango Delta, Botswana' -gravity southwest -annotate +70+125 'Annual flooding frequency from AVHRR images' -annotate +285+90 '1992' \( -size 606x600 xc:none -font Trebuchet -pointsize 100 -gravity center -draw &quot;fill rgba(120,120,120,0.20) text 2,2 'KARTTUR' fill rgba(225,225,225,0.20) text -2,-2 'KARTTUR' fill grey text 0,0 'KARTTUR' &quot; -transparent grey -fuzz 90% \) -composite -quality 72 floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1992_fews.jpg
convert floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1992_fews.jpg -resize 240x floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1992_fews-ql.jpg

/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -overwrite  -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/tgdata/old_CDs/okavango/delta/HYDRO/h2o_1993_noaa temp.tif
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate -srcwin 0 0 606 600 -a_ullr 556750.0 8000000.0 859750.0 7700000.0 temp.tif floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1993_fews.tif

/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1993_fews.vrt temp.tif
convert oka-pleasing_bg_landsat_500m.png \( temp.tif -alpha set -channel A -evaluate set 60% \) -gravity center -flatten temp.png
convert -crop 562x542+48+22 temp.png floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1993_fews.png
convert floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1993_fews.png -pointsize 24 -font Trebuchet -fill 'RGBA(0,10,200,1)' -gravity north -annotate -50+25 'Okavango Delta, Botswana' -gravity southwest -annotate +70+125 'Annual flooding frequency from AVHRR images' -annotate +285+90 '1993' \( -size 606x600 xc:none -font Trebuchet -pointsize 100 -gravity center -draw &quot;fill rgba(120,120,120,0.20) text 2,2 'KARTTUR' fill rgba(225,225,225,0.20) text -2,-2 'KARTTUR' fill grey text 0,0 'KARTTUR' &quot; -transparent grey -fuzz 90% \) -composite -quality 72 floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1993_fews.jpg
convert floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1993_fews.jpg -resize 240x floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1993_fews-ql.jpg

/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -overwrite  -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/tgdata/old_CDs/okavango/delta/HYDRO/h2o_1995_noaa temp.tif
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate -srcwin 0 0 606 600 -a_ullr 556750.0 8000000.0 859750.0 7700000.0 temp.tif floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1995_fews.tif

/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1995_fews.vrt temp.tif
convert oka-pleasing_bg_landsat_500m.png \( temp.tif -alpha set -channel A -evaluate set 60% \) -gravity center -flatten temp.png
convert -crop 562x542+48+22 temp.png floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1995_fews.png
convert floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1995_fews.png -pointsize 24 -font Trebuchet -fill 'RGBA(0,10,200,1)' -gravity north -annotate -50+25 'Okavango Delta, Botswana' -gravity southwest -annotate +70+125 'Annual flooding frequency from AVHRR images' -annotate +285+90 '1995' \( -size 606x600 xc:none -font Trebuchet -pointsize 100 -gravity center -draw &quot;fill rgba(120,120,120,0.20) text 2,2 'KARTTUR' fill rgba(225,225,225,0.20) text -2,-2 'KARTTUR' fill grey text 0,0 'KARTTUR' &quot; -transparent grey -fuzz 90% \) -composite -quality 72 floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1995_fews.jpg
convert floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1995_fews.jpg -resize 240x floodfreq_avhrr_okaswamps_1995_fews-ql.jpg
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;landsat-quicklooks&quot;&gt;Landsat quicklooks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FROM the USGS online archive of available Landsat scenes back in 2000, we grabbed all the quicklooks we could find (totaling 92). Using an automatic clustering routine followed by manual selection of water classes we created water masks for each individual scene. The scene data is stored under “./old_CDs/okavango/VAIO/Data_spatial/flood/ArcView_Landsat_1972-2004/scenes”. To create a shell script file for importing the data, run the python module &lt;em&gt;ImportLandsatArcViewDaily&lt;/em&gt;. The shell script that is created is called &lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;landsat-scenes_flooding-fix.sh&lt;/span&gt;. The flood masks for all scene are are available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/flooding&quot;&gt;Karttur’s GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;monthly-composites&quot;&gt;Monthly composites&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For months with complete (or almost complete) coverage over the Okavango, we created monthly inundation masks. The monthly composites are available under “./old_CDs/okavango/VAIO/Data_spatial/flood/ArcView_Landsat_1972-2004/Mosaics”. To create a shell script file for importing the data, run the python module &lt;em&gt;ImportLandsatArcViewMonthly&lt;/em&gt;. The shell script that is created is called &lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;landsat-monthly_flooding-fix.sh&lt;/span&gt;. The flood masks for all available months are on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/flooding&quot;&gt;Karttur’s GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;. The script includes the ImageMagick commands for creating quicklook figures and they are all (12 in total) shown in the &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr&quot;&gt;blog post on AVHRR, ATSR and Landsat quicklook images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;annual-max-floods&quot;&gt;Annual max floods&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the scene data, the annual maximum extent (accumulated) of the inundation area were extracted. These annual composites are available under “./old_CDs/okavango/VAIO/Data_spatial/flood/ArcView_Landsat_1972-2004/Annual_max_flood”. To create a shell script file for importing the data, run the python module &lt;em&gt;ImportLandsatArcViewAnnual&lt;/em&gt;. The shell script that is created is called &lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;landsat-annual_flooding-fix.sh&lt;/span&gt;. The flood masks for all annual composites are are available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/flooding&quot;&gt;Karttur’s GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;. The script includes the ImageMagick commands for creating quicklook figures and they are all (8 in total) shown in the &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr&quot;&gt;blog post on AVHRR, ATSR and Landsat quicklook images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;atsr&quot;&gt;ATSR&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 1999 and 2000 we acquired 28 ATSR scenes over the Okavango. The raw scenes are available under “./old_CDs/okavango/VAIO/Data_spatial/flood/Work/atsr/ermapper”. To import them run the python function &lt;em&gt;ImportErsRawATSR&lt;/em&gt;. The script requires a template file for creating Ermapper &lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;.ers&lt;/span&gt; headers (&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;template.ers&lt;/span&gt;). The script then produces a shell script file, &lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;atsr-rawbands.sh&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ATSR scenes (with 7 bands), cut to fit the larger Okavango area are available in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/flooding&quot;&gt;Karttur’s GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;unsupervised-classification&quot;&gt;Unsupervised classification&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each ATSR scene the unsupervised clustering is also available, under “./old_CDs/okavango/VAIO/Data_spatial/flood/Work/atsr/idriATSR”. Create the shell script (&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;atsr_clustering-fix.sh&amp;lt;/file&amp;gt;)for importing the clustered ATSR data by running the python function &lt;em&gt;CreateErsHeadersATSR&lt;/em&gt;. All the clusters are availabale are available in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/flooding&quot;&gt;Karttur’s GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;atsr-floodmasks&quot;&gt;ATSR floodmasks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The images with the classification of the clusters into floodmasks is available under “./old_CDs/okavango/Delta_2/flood”. The import function is the same as for the clusters, and the python function (&lt;em&gt;CreateErsHeadersATSR&lt;/em&gt;) must be manually edited to work for each import. All the masks are availabale are available in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/flooding&quot;&gt;Karttur’s GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;flood-accuracy-evaluations&quot;&gt;Flood accuracy evaluations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In total, the accuracy of the flood masks were tested comparing 12 dates. For each of these 12 dates we created flood masks from data representing two different sensors, either AVHRR versus ATSR, or AVHRR versus Landsat. The cross tabulation images are available under “./old_CDs/okavango/VAIO/Data_spatial/flood/Work”.  Create the shell script (&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;crosstab_flooding-fix.sh&amp;lt;/file&amp;gt;) for importing the cross correlation data by running the python function &lt;em&gt;CreateErsHeadersCrossTab&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The generated script includes the ImageMagick commands for creating the quicklooks that are shown in the blog post on &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-avhrr/&quot;&gt;AVHRR, ATSR and Landsat quicklook images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flood-frequency-at-high-spatial-resolution&quot;&gt;Flood frequency at high spatial resolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combining the flood frequency data with the Landsat composition, a flood mask in 28.5 spatial resolution could be created. The script for importing it and fit it exactly to the pleasing landsat composite and the landcover classification:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#Import flooding at 28.5 m
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -overwrite -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/Pegasus6/oldstuff/Pegasus6/old_CDs/okavango/delta/HYDRO/FLLOOD28 FLLOOD28.tif
#Translate to fit the landcover
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate -a_ullr 580276.5443080846453086 7988350.1142306961119175 869808.0443080846453086 7718768.6142306961119175 FLLOOD28.tif floodfreq_combo_okaswamps_1992-2000_28m.tif

#Create a virtual copy
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalbuildvrt highresol_floodmap.vrt floodfreq_combo_okaswamps_1992-2000_28m.tif

#Manually add colors, then recreate a color ramped flooding image
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate highresol_floodmap.vrt floodfreq_multisource_okaswamps_1992-2000_28m.tif

#Craete a small image
convert -resize 800x +repage floodfreq_multisource_okaswamps_1992-2000_28m.tif floodfreq_multisource_okaswamps_1992-2000_m.png

#Overlay flood and pleasing landsat
convert natcol_lt05_okaswamps_199407_m.png \( floodfreq_multisource_okaswamps_1992-2000_m.png -alpha set -channel A -evaluate set 60% \) -gravity center -flatten temp.png

#Add text to the overlay
convert temp.png -pointsize 30 -font Trebuchet -fill 'RGBA(0,10,200,1)' -gravity north -annotate -100+10 'Okavango Delta, Botswana' -gravity southwest -annotate +365+65 'Multi source flooding frequency' -annotate +515+30 '1972-2000' \( -size 606x600 xc:none -font Trebuchet -pointsize 140 -gravity center -draw &quot;fill rgba(120,120,120,0.20) text 2,2 'KARTTUR' fill rgba(225,225,225,0.20) text -2,-2 'KARTTUR' fill grey text 0,0 'KARTTUR' &quot; -transparent grey -fuzz 90% \) -composite -quality 80 floodfreq_multisource_okaswamps_1992-2000_m.jpg
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;geophysiology&quot;&gt;Geophysiology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shell script for importing and arranging the geophysiology spatial layers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# geophsysiological regions
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:4326 geophysiology_wits_okaswamps_1994_pub.shp &quot;/Volumes/tgdata/old_CDs/okavango/Delta_2/flood/physiographic_regions.shp&quot;

# arc maximum delta
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:4326 maxflood-arc_wits_okaswamps_1994_pub.shp &quot;/Volumes/tgdata/old_CDs/okavango/VAIO/Data_spatial/Hydrology/ArcView/oka_delta_arc.shp&quot;

#Shape files of flooding frequency
#50%
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:4326 flooding-freq-50%_satimg_okaswamps_1972-2000_0.shp &quot;/Volumes/tgdata/old_CDs/okavango/islands/delta/HYDRO/h2o_50%_of_time.shp&quot;
#65%
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:4326 flooding-freq-65%_satimg_okaswamps_1972-2000_0.shp &quot;/Volumes/tgdata/old_CDs/okavango/islands/delta/HYDRO/h2o_65%_of_time.shp&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ecoregion-classification&quot;&gt;Ecoregion classification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ecoregion map was done by combining multi-source datasets using expert rules (if … then … else …). Almost 20 year later I have not been able to dis-entangle the input data and the rules, but the final ecoregion map can be imported and symbolized through these GDAL commands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#Import the original landcover classification as a virtual layer
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalbuildvrt oka_lc.vrt /Volumes/tgdata/old_CDs/okavango/okaCD1.1/OKAVANGO/Delta/landcover/rawdata/oka_delta_landcover_classification.img.ers

#To put colors and labels the vrt dataset must be manually edited

#Warp the virutal layer to EPSG:32734
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -tr 28.50 28.50 -overwrite oka-lc_karttur_okaswamps_1994_pub.vrt landcover_lt05_okaswamps_1994_pub.tif -t_srs EPSG:32734
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The edited virtual layer with labels and colors added:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;VRTDataset rasterXSize=&quot;10159&quot; rasterYSize=&quot;9458&quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;SRS&amp;gt;PROJCS[&quot;SUTM34&quot;,GEOGCS[&quot;CAPE DATUM&quot;,DATUM[&quot;CAPE&quot;,SPHEROID[&quot;CLA80MOD&quot;,6378249.145,293.465]],PRIMEM[&quot;Greenwich&quot;,0],UNIT[&quot;degree&quot;,0.0174532925199433]],PROJECTION[&quot;Transverse_Mercator&quot;],PARAMETER[&quot;latitude_of_origin&quot;,0],PARAMETER[&quot;central_meridian&quot;,21],PARAMETER[&quot;scale_factor&quot;,0.9996],PARAMETER[&quot;false_easting&quot;,500000],PARAMETER[&quot;false_northing&quot;,10000000],UNIT[&quot;Meter&quot;,1]]&amp;lt;/SRS&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;GeoTransform&amp;gt;  5.8027850000000000e+05,  2.8500000000000000e+01,  0.0000000000000000e+00,  7.9885245000000000e+06,  0.0000000000000000e+00, -2.8500000000000000e+01&amp;lt;/GeoTransform&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;VRTRasterBand dataType=&quot;Byte&quot; band=&quot;1&quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;SimpleSource&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;SourceFilename relativeToVRT=&quot;1&quot;&amp;gt;oka_delta_landcover_classification.img.ers&amp;lt;/SourceFilename&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;SourceBand&amp;gt;1&amp;lt;/SourceBand&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;SourceProperties RasterXSize=&quot;10159&quot; RasterYSize=&quot;9458&quot; DataType=&quot;Byte&quot; BlockXSize=&quot;10159&quot; BlockYSize=&quot;1&quot; /&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;SrcRect xOff=&quot;0&quot; yOff=&quot;0&quot; xSize=&quot;10159&quot; ySize=&quot;9458&quot; /&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;DstRect xOff=&quot;0&quot; yOff=&quot;0&quot; xSize=&quot;10159&quot; ySize=&quot;9458&quot; /&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/SimpleSource&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;CategoryNames&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Category&amp;gt;Water&amp;lt;/Category&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Category&amp;gt;Permanent wetland (dominated by papyrus and reed)&amp;lt;/Category&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Category&amp;gt;primary floodplain (inundated 30 - 80 % of time)&amp;lt;/Category&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Category&amp;gt;Secondary floodplain (inundated 10 - 50 % of time)&amp;lt;/Category&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Category&amp;gt;Wet meadow (Grassland with occasional flooding)&amp;lt;/Category&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Category&amp;gt;Riverine forest&amp;lt;/Category&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Category&amp;gt;Pan/Dry grasspand (with occasional flooding)&amp;lt;/Category&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Category&amp;gt;Dry woodland (dominated by Acacia)&amp;lt;/Category&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Category&amp;gt;Dry woodland (dominated by Mopane)&amp;lt;/Category&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Category&amp;gt;Dry woodland (dominated by Combretum)&amp;lt;/Category&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Category&amp;gt;Grassland&amp;lt;/Category&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Category&amp;gt;Pan/grassland (non-flooded)&amp;lt;/Category&amp;gt;
	&amp;lt;/CategoryNames&amp;gt;
	&amp;lt;ColorTable&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Entry c1=&quot;0&quot; c2=&quot;0&quot; c3=&quot;0&quot; c4=&quot;255&quot;/&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Entry c1=&quot;92&quot; c2=&quot;0&quot; c3=&quot;231&quot; c4=&quot;255&quot;/&amp;gt;
  		&amp;lt;Entry c1=&quot;0&quot; c2=&quot;131&quot; c3=&quot;128&quot; c4=&quot;255&quot;/&amp;gt;¨
  		&amp;lt;Entry c1=&quot;0&quot; c2=&quot;186&quot; c3=&quot;152&quot; c4=&quot;255&quot;/&amp;gt;¨
  		&amp;lt;Entry c1=&quot;162&quot; c2=&quot;143&quot; c3=&quot;0&quot; c4=&quot;255&quot;/&amp;gt;¨
  		&amp;lt;Entry c1=&quot;221&quot; c2=&quot;228&quot; c3=&quot;0&quot; c4=&quot;255&quot;/&amp;gt;¨
  		&amp;lt;Entry c1=&quot;0&quot; c2=&quot;109&quot; c3=&quot;0&quot; c4=&quot;255&quot;/&amp;gt;¨
  		&amp;lt;Entry c1=&quot;228&quot; c2=&quot;227&quot; c3=&quot;138&quot; c4=&quot;255&quot;/&amp;gt;¨
  		&amp;lt;Entry c1=&quot;133&quot; c2=&quot;180&quot; c3=&quot;0&quot; c4=&quot;255&quot;/&amp;gt;¨
  		&amp;lt;Entry c1=&quot;118&quot; c2=&quot;161&quot; c3=&quot;0&quot; c4=&quot;255&quot;/&amp;gt;¨
  		&amp;lt;Entry c1=&quot;135&quot; c2=&quot;181&quot; c3=&quot;0&quot; c4=&quot;255&quot;/&amp;gt;¨
  		&amp;lt;Entry c1=&quot;255&quot; c2=&quot;219&quot; c3=&quot;89&quot; c4=&quot;255&quot;/&amp;gt;¨
  		&amp;lt;Entry c1=&quot;254&quot; c2=&quot;254&quot; c3=&quot;189&quot; c4=&quot;189&quot;/&amp;gt;¨
	&amp;lt;/ColorTable&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/VRTRasterBand&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/VRTDataset&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The layers imported with the scripts above are availlable on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/geophysiology&quot;&gt;Karttur´s GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;regional-topography&quot;&gt;Regional topography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research that led to the regional topographic maps over the Okavango and surrounding regions was based on a limited sets of elevation data, plus the Landsat color composite (see above). The study led to a large set of datasets, all listed and available for download in the blog post on &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-dem/&quot;&gt;Regional topography&lt;/a&gt; post. The scripts for converting the old data to updated formats are summarized here. Most of the data are re-organized using the python module &lt;span class=&quot;package&quot;&gt;geoimagine.okavango.dem&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elevation-datasets&quot;&gt;Elevation datasets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four different sources of point elevation data were used for interpolating a DEM in 500 m spatial resolution, table 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 2. Point elevation datasets used for creating the 500 m resolution Digital Elevation Model over the larger Okavango area.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Dataset&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;description&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;gps-grav-survey&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Gravity survey with differential GPS positioning&lt;br /&gt;Geological Survey of Botswana&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;beacons&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Trigonemetric beacons identified from official Botswana maps&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;UCT-GPS&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Differential GPS positioning along major channels of the Okavango swamps&lt;br /&gt; University of Cape Town&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;DCW&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Beacon heights in the Namibian part of Linyanti&lt;br /&gt;Digital Chart of the World (DCW)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;gps-grav-survey&lt;/em&gt; is available under “./Okavango/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_all_grav/dem_all_grav.shp”, to import it call the python function &lt;em&gt;CheckFixDBFptElev&lt;/em&gt; (direct or via &lt;em&gt;CheckFixDBFptElevIni&lt;/em&gt;). The expected attributes to find in the layer &lt;em&gt;dem_all_grav.shp&lt;/em&gt; are hardcoded in &lt;em&gt;CheckFixDBFptElev&lt;/em&gt; so you can not alter any input names. The &lt;em&gt;beacons&lt;/em&gt; dataset is available under “./Okavango/oka-dem-fixed/dem_ptdata/beacon_tm_ortho/beacon_tm_ortho.shp”. The other datasets (&lt;em&gt;UCT-GPS&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;DCW&lt;/em&gt;) only covers a single subregion each and are available as sub-regional datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regionalization&quot;&gt;Regionalization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The larger Okavango region is clearly defined by fault lines, but with incised river beds. Table 3 lists the support layers used for creating the Okavango DEM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
Table 3. Okavango data layers of fault lines, river channels and elevation  regionalizations.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Layer content&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/support/fault-lines_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.zip&quot;&gt;fault-lines_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Fault lines&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/support/rivers-channels_karttur_okaswamps_0_digitized.zip&quot;&gt;rivers-channels_karttur_okaswamps_0_digitized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;River channels&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/geophysiology/geophysiology_wits_okaswamps_1994_pub.zip&quot;&gt;geophysiology_wits_okaswamps_1994_pub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Geophysiological regions of the Okavango swmaps&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../docs/dem/support/elev-regions_karttur_okaswamps_0_4demcreate.zip&quot;&gt;elev-regions_karttur_okaswamps_0_4demcreate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Elevation regions&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original regionalization data were manually fixed in July 2019; the fault lines where updated and labels added, the river dataset was not updates but the regional layer was cleaned and the sub-regions joined to multi-polygons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regionalized-input-elevation-datasets&quot;&gt;Regionalized input elevation datasets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regional Okavango DEM was generated dividing the area in 4 sub-regions. The elevation point data used as input for the kriging interpolation of the DEM are supplied per region and source dataset and available in the &lt;a href=&quot;../oka-dem/&quot;&gt;Regional DEM&lt;/a&gt; post, or from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/dem/input/&quot;&gt;Karttur’s GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To import the (partly organized) original data, run the python function &lt;em&gt;CheckFixDBFptElevIni&lt;/em&gt; and use the file listing all the regionalized data source and destination files (dem_gen_pt_shape_files.txt) as input:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_gen_nv_grav/dem_gen_nv_grav.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_gen_delta_grav/dem_gen_delta_grav.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_gen_kun_grav/dem_gen_kun_grav.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_gen_se_grav/dem_gen_se_grav.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka/elev-pt-subreg_gps-grav-survey_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_gen_delta_bb/dem_gen_delta_bb.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_gen_kun_bb/dem_gen_kun_bb.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_kunyere-trappa.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_gen_nv_bb/dem_gen_nv_bb.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_gen_se_bb/dem_gen_se_bb.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka/elev-pt-subreg_beacons_okaswamps_2000_se-drylands.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_gen_delta_uct/dem_gen_delta_uct.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka/elev-pt-subreg_gps-uct_okaswamps_2000_oka-wetlands.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_gen_linyanti/dem_gen_linyanti.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka/elev-pt-subreg_dcw_okaswamps_2000_nw-drylands.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_gen_remain_bb/dem_gen_remain_bb.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka/elev-pt-unused_beacons_okaswamps_2000_all-regions.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_all_grav/dem_all_grav.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka/elev-pt_gps-grav-survey_botswana_2000_bw-geosurvey.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_gen_areas_pts/dem_pt_all/dem_pt_all.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka/elev-pt_all_botswana_2000_no-pub.shp
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The input names are hardcoded in the function (&lt;em&gt;CheckFixDBFptElevIni&lt;/em&gt;) and you can not change the input names, then the attribute fixing will not work. If done correctly, you will get all the regionalized point data in one go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okavango-dem&quot;&gt;Okavango DEM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Digital Elevation Model (DEM) for the larger Okavango region was constructed by joining the kriging interpolated DEMs of the respective subregion. I can not find the individual sub-regional DEMs, but the combined DEM, along with estimated kriging accuracies is available. To organzie properly, run the following script:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -tr 500 500 -overwrite -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/dem_0720_00 dem_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.tif
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -tr 500 500  -overwrite -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-more/arcview/oka_dem_err dem-sd_wits_okaswamps_0_v2001.tif
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this raster DEM the contour lines were extracted, but must have been manually edited to fit heights and troughs. &lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;, that I also edited the contour lines in 2019 so re-running the import function will &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; lead to an exact copy of the existing layer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 elev-contours_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/oka_contours.shp&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-okavango-alluvial-fan&quot;&gt;The Okavango alluvial fan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vector data related to the Okavango alluvial fan was also edited in July 2019, fine tuning the extent of the fan surface (fan origin and fan iso-distance lines were not changed). To import the original fan vector data run the shell script:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#fan_area.shp: NOTE that the area is updated compared to the source layer
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 alluvial-fan_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/fan_area.shp&quot;

#fan_isolines_2.shp:
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 alluvial-fan-isodist_karttur_okaswamps_0_fromapex.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/fan isolines 2.shp&quot;

#fan_origin.shp
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 alluvial-fan-apex_karttur_okaswamps_0_v2001.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/fan origin.shp&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When re-organzing the data in 2019 I could not find theoretical DEM for the perfectly conical surface of the alluvial fan. Instead I created a new conical DEM and a new residual for the difference between theoretical cone and observed DEM over the alluvial fan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;/#Theoretical cone DEM
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_calc.py -A alluvial-fan-distance_wits_okaswamps_0_fromapex.tif --outfile=alluvial-fan-cone-dem_karttur_okasvamps_0_v2001.tif  --calc=&quot;981.05-(42/160000)*A&quot; --NoDataValue=0

#Difference between observed DEM and theoertical cone
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_calc.py -A dem_wits_okaswamps_0_0720.tif -B newcone.tif --outfile=alluvial-fan-residual-dem_karttur_okasvamps_0_v2001.tif  --calc=&quot;A-B&quot; --NoDataValue=0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lake-ngami-regional-dem&quot;&gt;Lake Ngami Regional DEM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Lake Ngami region a special DEM was created back in 2000, and re-organized in 2019. &lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt; that during the 2019 re-organization I edited some of the imported layers and re-running the GDAL functions in the script will not generate identical layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#Shoreline point data
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/Ngami/ngami_shore_dem.shp&quot;

#Palaeo shoreline
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 palaeo-shore-arc_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/Ngami paleo shoreline.shp&quot;

#central axis
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 centreline_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/ngami/ngami_centroid.shp&quot;

#Iso distance along centroid axis
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 isodist_karttur_lakengami_0_centreline.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/ngami/ngami_isodist.shp&quot;

#ngami_contours.shp:
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 elev-contours_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_ngami/oka_topo_ngami_contours/oka_topo_ngami_contours.shp&quot;

#ngami_grav_dem.shp: The data used for generation Ngami DEM
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 elev-pt_gps_lakengami_1999_grav-survey.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/Ngami/ngami_grav_dem.shp&quot;

#ngami_beacon_dem
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 elev-pt_beacon_lakengami_0_frommap.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/Ngami/ngami_beacon_dem.shp&quot;

#DEM
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -tr 500 500 -overwrite -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/Ngami/ngami_dem dem_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.tif

#Estimated error from kriging interpolation
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -tr 500 500  -overwrite -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/Ngami/ngami_sd dem-sd_karttur_lakengami_0_v2001.tif

#Natural color Landsat image
#Ngami pleasing image at 28 m  (from ecw - only source I can find)
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -overwrite -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/tgdata/old_CDs/okavango/okaCD1.1/OKAVANGO/Delta/landcover/graphics/ngami_pleasing_tm.ecw natcol_lt05_lakengami_199407_rgb-bands.tif

#Use ImageMagick to quantisize to 256 colors
convert natcol_lt05_lakengami_199407_rgb-bands.tif +dither  -colors 255  natcol_lt05_lakengami_199407_byte.png

#Convert back to Geotiff tiff
#/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate -a_srs EPSG:32734 -a_ullr 624161.4676754806423560 7760102.8934778925031424 715743.2956791395554319 7708511.9903688011690974  natcol_lt05_lakengami_199407_byte.png natcol_lt05_lakengami_199407_byte.tif
#60 m down
#100 m right
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate -a_srs EPSG:32734 -a_ullr 624261.4676754806423560 7760042.8934778925031424 715843.2956791395554319 7708451.9903688011690974  natcol_lt05_lakengami_199407_byte.png natcol_lt05_lakengami_199407_byte.tif
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mababe-depression-regional-dem&quot;&gt;Mababe depression Regional DEM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Mababe depression region a special DEM was created back in 2000. Run the script below to re-organize the Mababe Depression regional DEM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#Shoreline point data
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/mababe/mab_shore_dem.shp&quot;

#Palaeo shoreline
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 palaeo-shore-arc_karttur_mababedepr_0_pos-from-lt05.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/mababe/mab_shores.shp&quot;

#mababe_centroid.shp: central axis
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 centreline_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/mababe/mab_centroid.shp&quot;

#mab_isodist.shp: MABABE ISO distance along centroid axis
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 isodist_karttur_mababedepr_0_centreline.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_mababe/mab_isodist/mab_isodist.shp&quot;

#mababe_dem_contours.shp: This are the isohyeths from the DEM, without added other stuff
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 elev-contours_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_mababe/mababe_dem_contours/mababe_dem_contours.shp&quot;

#mababe_grav_tm.shp: The data used for generation Ngami DEM
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 elev-pt_gps_mababedepr_1999_grav-survey.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/mababe/mababe_grav_tm.shp&quot;

#DEM
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -tr 500 500 -overwrite -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/Mababe/mab_dem dem_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.tif

#Estimated error from kriging interpolation
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -tr 500 500  -overwrite -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-ArcView/Mababe/mab_sd dem-sd_karttur_mababedepr_0_v2001.tif

#Mababe pleasing image at 28 m  (from ecw - only source I can find)
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -overwrite -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/tgdata/old_CDs/okavango/okaCD1.1/OKAVANGO/Delta/landcover/graphics/mababe_pleasing_tm.ecw natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_rgb-bands.tif

#Use ImageMagick to quantisize to 256 colors
convert natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_rgb-bands.tif +dither  -colors 255  natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_byte.png

#Convert back to Geotiff tiff
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate -a_srs EPSG:32734 -a_ullr 794240.0542575517902151 7960587.5265753660351038 880258.8149869333719835 7859056.2679800735786557 natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_byte.png natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_byte.tif
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mkgadikgadi-ridge-region&quot;&gt;Mkgadikgadi Ridge Region&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also for the Mkgadikgadi Ridge Region a special DEM was created back in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#Shoreline point data
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 elev-pt-palaeo-shore_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-more/arcview/mkgadi_dem_points.shp&quot;

#Palaeo shoreline
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 palaeo-shore-arc_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_pos-from-lt05.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-more/arcview/mkgadi_shore.shp&quot;

#mkgadi_isodist.shp: Mkgadi ISO dist from Boteti
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 isodist_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_centreline.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-more/arcview/mkgadi_isodist.shp&quot;

#mkgadi_contours.shp: This are the isohyeths from the DEM, without added other stuff
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 elev-contours_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_v2001.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-more/arcvie/mkgadi_contours.shp&quot;

#mababe_grav_tm.shp: The data used for generation Ngami DEM
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/ogr2ogr -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 elev-pt_gps_mkgadiridge_1999_grav-survey.shp &quot;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-more/arcview/grav_tm_mkgadi.shp&quot;

#DEM
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -tr 500 500 -overwrite -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-more/arcview/mkgadi_dem demtemp.tif
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate -a_ullr 830288.515 7816312.742 885794.137 7669802.090 demtemp.tif dem_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_pub.tif

#the error raster, for some strange, but unknown, reason is one row and one column smaller and must be fitted.
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -overwrite -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-more/arcview/mkgadi_err errtemp.tif
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate -a_ullr 830288.515 7815812.742 885294.137 7669802.090 errtemp.tif dem-sd_karttur_mkgadiridge_0_pub.tif

#Mababe pleasing image at 28 m  (from ecw - only source I can find)
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdalwarp -overwrite -s_srs &quot;+proj=utm +zone=34 +south +ellps=clrk80 +units=m +no_defs&quot; -t_srs EPSG:32734 /Volumes/tgdata/old_CDs/okavango/okaCD1.1/OKAVANGO/Delta/landcover/graphics/mkgadikgadi_pleasing_tm.ecw natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_rgb-bands2.tif

#Use ImageMagick to quantisize to 256 colors
convert natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_rgb-bands2.tif +dither  -colors 255  natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_byte.png

#Convert back to Geotiff tiff
/Library/Frameworks/GDAL.framework/Versions/2.4/Programs/gdal_translate -a_srs EPSG:32734 -a_ullr 794240.0542575517902151 7960587.5265753660351038 880258.8149869333719835 7859056.2679800735786557 natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_byte.png natcol_lt05_mababedepr_199407_byte.tif
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okavango-swamps-water-level-dem&quot;&gt;Okavango swamps water level DEM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The source data for generating the water surface DEM, from surveys done by Univeristy of Capte Town, are imported with python function &lt;em&gt;CheckFixDBFwaterElevIni&lt;/em&gt;. A text file is used for defining source and destionation layers (&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;dem_gen_water_shape_files.txt&lt;/span&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_ptdata/uct_gps_h2o_94/uct_gps_h2o_94.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka_water/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1994_v2001.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_ptdata/uct_gps_h2o_95_tm/uct_gps_h2o_95_tm.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka_water/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1995_v2001.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_ptdata/uct_gps_h2o_96/uct_gps_h2o_96.shp,/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka_water/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1996_v2001.shp

/Volumes/karttur/oka-dem-fixed/dem_ptdata/uct_gps_h2o_98_tm/uct_gps_h2o_98_tm.shp,uct_gps_h2o_98_tm/Volumes/karttur/okavango/dem/oka_water/elev-pt-water_gps-uct_okaswamps_1998_v2001.shp
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attribute table fixing is hardcoded in python and you can not change the source file names, then it does not work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karttur/okavango/tree/gh-pages/docs/scripts/&quot;&gt;Github repositories with scripts for re-organizing the Okavango spatial data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Okavango" /><category term="Spatial data" /><category term="organization" /><summary type="html">Re-organization of the Okavango spatial data created during my post-doc period at University of the Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, South Africa, 1999-2001.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/avg-trmm-3b43v7-precip_3B43_trmm_2001-2016_A" /></entry></feed>